 The <ORGANIZATION>Project Gutenberg EBook of Dubliners</ORGANIZATION>, by <PERSON>James Joyce</PERSON>



Title: Dubliners

Author: <PERSON>James Joyce</PERSON>

Release Date: September, 2001 [EBook #2814]
Last Updated: April 1, 2016

Language: English

Character set encoding: UTF-8

*** START OF THIS PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK DUBLINERS ***



Produced by <PERSON>David Reed</PERSON>, <PERSON>Karol Pietrzak</PERSON>, and <PERSON>David Widger</PERSON>



DUBLINERS

By <PERSON>James Joyce



Contents


THE</PERSON> SISTERS

AN ENCOUNTER

ARABY

EVELINE

AFTER THE RACE

TWO GALLANTS

THE BOARDING HOUSE

A LITTLE CLOUD

COUNTERPARTS

CLAY

A PAINFUL CASE

IVY DAY IN THE COMMITTEE ROOM

A MOTHER

GRACE

THE DEAD



DUBLINERS



THE SISTERS

THERE was no hope for him this time: it was the third stroke. Night
I would see the reflection of candles on the darkened blind for I knew
that two candles must be set at the head of a corpse. He had often said
to me: "I am not long for this world," and I had thought his words idle.
Now I knew they were true. Every night as I gazed up at the window
I said softly to myself the word paralysis. It had always sounded
simony in the Catechism. But now it sounded to me like the name of some
maleficent and sinful being. It filled me with fear, and yet I longed to

Old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> was sitting at the fire, smoking, when I came downstairs
to supper. While my aunt was ladling out my stirabout he said, as if
returning to some former remark of his:

"No, I wouldn't say he was exactly ... but there was something queer ...
there was something uncanny about him. I'll tell you my opinion...."


"I have my own theory about it," he said. "I think it was one of those
uncle saw me staring and said to me:

"Well, so your old friend is gone, you'll be sorry to hear."

"Who?" said I.

"Father <PERSON>Flynn</PERSON>."

"Is he dead?"

"Mr <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> here has just told us. He was passing by the house."

I knew that I was under observation so I continued eating as if the news
had not interested me. My uncle explained to old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON>.

"The youngster and he were great friends. The old chap taught him a

"God have mercy on his soul," said my aunt piously.

Old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> looked at me for a while. I felt that his little beady black
plate. He returned to his pipe and finally spat rudely into the grate.

a man like that."

"How do you mean, Mr <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON>?" asked my aunt.

"What I mean is," said old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON>, "it's bad for children. My idea is:
let a young lad run about and play with young lads of his own age and
not be.... Am I right, <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>?"

"That's my principle, too," said my uncle. "Let him learn to box his
corner. That's what I'm always saying to that Rosicrucian there: take
exercise. Why, when I was a nipper every morning of my life I had a cold
bath, winter and summer. And that's what stands to me now. Education
is all very fine and large.... Mr <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> might take a pick of that leg
mutton," he added to my aunt.

"No, no, not for me," said old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON>.


"It's bad for children," said old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON>, "because their minds are so
anger. Tiresome old red-nosed imbecile!

It was late when I fell asleep. Though I was angry with old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> for
alluding to me as a child, I puzzled my head to extract meaning from his
unfinished sentences. In the dark of my room I imagined that I saw again
the heavy grey face of the paralytic. I drew the blankets over my head
and tried to think of Christmas. But the grey face still followed me. It
murmured; and I understood that it desired to confess something. I felt
I found it waiting for me. It began to confess to me in a murmuring
voice and I wondered why it smiled continually and why the lips were so
moist with spittle. But then I remembered that it had died of paralysis
and I felt that I too was smiling feebly as if to absolve the simoniac
of his sin.

The next morning after breakfast I went down to look at the little house
in <LOCATION>Great Britain Street</LOCATION>. It was an unassuming shop, registered under
the vague name of _Drapery_. The drapery consisted mainly of children's
bootees and umbrellas; and on ordinary days a notice used to hang in the
window, saying: _Umbrellas Re-covered_. No notice was visible now for
the shutters were up. A crape bouquet was tied to the door-knocker with
on the crape. I also approached and read:

July 1st, 1895 The Rev. <PERSON>James Flynn</PERSON> (formerly of <PERSON>S. Catherine</PERSON>'s Church,
<LOCATION>Meath Street</LOCATION>), aged sixty-five years. _<PERSON>R. I. P.</PERSON>_

The reading of the card persuaded me that he was dead and I was
disturbed to find myself at check. Had he not been dead I would have
gone into the little dark room behind the shop to find him sitting in
his arm-chair by the fire, nearly smothered in his great-coat. Perhaps
my aunt would have given me a packet of High Toast for him and this
present would have roused him from his stupefied doze. It was always I
the floor. Even as he raised his large trembling hand to his nose little
clouds of smoke dribbled through his fingers over the front of his coat.
It may have been these constant showers of snuff which gave his ancient
priestly garments their green faded look for the red handkerchief,
blackened, as it always was, with the snuff-stains of a week, with which
he tried to brush away the fallen grains, was quite inefficacious.

walked away slowly along the sunny side of the street, reading all
the theatrical advertisements in the shopwindows as I went. I found it
strange that neither I nor the day seemed in a mourning mood and I felt
even annoyed at discovering in myself a sensation of freedom as if I had
been freed from something by his death. I wondered at this for, as my
studied in the Irish college in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> and he had taught me to pronounce
Latin properly. He had told me stories about the catacombs and about
<PERSON>Napoleon Bonaparte</PERSON>, and he had explained to me the meaning of the
different ceremonies of the Mass and of the different vestments worn
by the priest. Sometimes he had amused himself by putting difficult
questions to me, asking me what one should do in certain circumstances
or whether such and such sins were mortal or venial or only
imperfections. His questions showed me how complex and mysterious were
certain institutions of the Church which I had always regarded as
the simplest acts. The duties of the priest towards the Eucharist and
towards the secrecy of the confessional seemed so grave to me that I
wondered how anybody had ever found in himself the courage to undertake
them; and I was not surprised when he told me that the fathers of the
<ORGANIZATION>Church</ORGANIZATION> had written books as thick as the _<ORGANIZATION>Post Office Directory</ORGANIZATION>_ and
as closely printed as the law notices in the newspaper, elucidating all
these intricate questions. Often when I thought of this I could make
no answer or only a very foolish and halting one upon which he used
to smile and nod his head twice or thrice. Sometimes he used to put me
smiled he used to uncover his big discoloured teeth and let his tongue
lie upon his lower lip--a habit which had made me feel uneasy in the
beginning of our acquaintance before I knew him well.

As I walked along in the sun I remembered old <PERSON>Cotter</PERSON>'s words and tried
to remember what had happened afterwards in the dream. I remembered
that I had noticed long velvet curtains and a swinging lamp of antique
fashion. I felt that I had been very far away, in some land where the
customs were strange--in <LOCATION>Persia</LOCATION>, I thought.... But I could not remember
the end of the dream.

In the evening my aunt took me with her to visit the house of mourning.
It was after sunset; but the window-panes of the houses that looked
to the west reflected the tawny gold of a great bank of clouds. <PERSON>Nannie</PERSON>
received us in the hall; and, as it would have been unseemly to have
shouted at her, my aunt shook hands with her for all. The old woman
above the level of the banister-rail. At the first landing she stopped
dead-room. My aunt went in and the old woman, seeing that I hesitated to
enter, began to beckon to me again repeatedly with her hand.

I went in on tiptoe. The room through the lace end of the blind was
suffused with dusky golden light amid which the candles looked like pale
thin flames. He had been coffined. <PERSON>Nannie</PERSON> gave the lead and we three
knelt down at the foot of the bed. I pretended to pray but I could not
gather my thoughts because the old woman's mutterings distracted me. I
noticed how clumsily her skirt was hooked at the back and how the heels
of her cloth boots were trodden down all to one side. The fancy came to
me that the old priest was smiling as he lay there in his coffin.

But no. When we rose and went up to the head of the bed I saw that he
was not smiling. There he lay, solemn and copious, vested as for the
altar, his large hands loosely retaining a chalice. His face was very
truculent, grey and massive, with black cavernous nostrils and circled
by a scanty white fur. There was a heavy odour in the room--the flowers.

We blessed ourselves and came away. In the little room downstairs we
found <PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> seated in his arm-chair in state. I groped my way towards my
usual chair in the corner while <PERSON>Nannie</PERSON> went to the sideboard and brought
out a decanter of sherry and some wine-glasses. She set these on the
table and invited us to take a little glass of wine. Then, at her
sister's bidding, she filled out the sherry into the glasses and passed
them to us. She pressed me to take some cream crackers also but I
declined because I thought I would make too much noise eating them. She
seemed to be somewhat disappointed at my refusal and went over quietly
to the sofa where she sat down behind her sister. No one spoke: we all
gazed at the empty fireplace.

My aunt waited until <PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> sighed and then said:

"Ah, well, he's gone to a better world."

<PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> sighed again and bowed her head in assent. My aunt fingered the
stem of her wine-glass before sipping a little.

"Did he ... peacefully?" she asked.

"Oh, quite peacefully, ma'am," said <PERSON>Eliza</PERSON>. "You couldn't tell when the
breath went out of him. He had a beautiful death, God be praised."

"And everything...?"

"Father <PERSON>O'Rourke</PERSON> was in with him a Tuesday and anointed him and prepared
him and all."

"He knew then?"

"He was quite resigned."

"He looks quite resigned," said my aunt.

"That's what the woman we had in to wash him said. She said he just
looked as if he was asleep, he looked that peaceful and resigned. No one
would think he'd make such a beautiful corpse."

"Yes, indeed," said my aunt.

She sipped a little more from her glass and said:

"Well, Miss <PERSON>Flynn</PERSON>, at any rate it must be a great comfort for you to
know that you did all you could for him. You were both very kind to him,
I must say."

<PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> smoothed her dress over her knees.

"Ah, poor <PERSON>James</PERSON>!" she said. "God knows we done all we could, as poor as
we are--we wouldn't see him want anything while he was in it."

<PERSON>Nannie</PERSON> had leaned her head against the sofa-pillow and seemed about to
fall asleep.

"There's poor <PERSON>Nannie</PERSON>," said <PERSON>Eliza</PERSON>, looking at her, "she's wore out. All
the work we had, she and me, getting in the woman to wash him and then
laying him out and then the coffin and then arranging about the <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION> in
the chapel. Only for Father <PERSON>O'Rourke</PERSON> I don't know what we'd have done
at all. It was him brought us all them flowers and them two candlesticks
out of the chapel and wrote out the notice for the _<PERSON>Freeman</PERSON>'s General_
and took charge of all the papers for the cemetery and poor <PERSON>James</PERSON>'s
insurance."

"Wasn't that good of him?" said my aunt.

<PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> closed her eyes and shook her head slowly.

"Ah, there's no friends like the old friends," she said, "when all is
said and done, no friends that a body can trust."

"Indeed, that's true," said my aunt. "And I'm sure now that he's gone to
his eternal reward he won't forget you and all your kindness to him."

"Ah, poor <PERSON>James</PERSON>!" said <PERSON>Eliza</PERSON>. "He was no great trouble to us. You
wouldn't hear him in the house any more than now. Still, I know he's
gone and all to that...."

"It's when it's all over that you'll miss him," said my aunt.

"I know that," said <PERSON>Eliza</PERSON>. "I won't be bringing him in his cup of
beef-tea any more, nor you, ma'am, sending him his snuff. Ah, poor
<PERSON>James</PERSON>!"

She stopped, as if she were communing with the past and then said
shrewdly:

"Mind you, I noticed there was something queer coming over him latterly.
Whenever I'd bring in his soup to him there I'd find him with his
breviary fallen to the floor, lying back in the chair and his mouth
open."

She laid a finger against her nose and frowned: then she continued:

"But still and all he kept on saying that before the summer was over
he'd go out for a drive one fine day just to see the old house again
where we were all born down in Irishtown and take me and <PERSON>Nannie</PERSON> with
him. If we could only get one of them new-fangled carriages that makes
no noise that <PERSON>Father O'Rourke</PERSON> told him about, them with the rheumatic
wheels, for the day cheap--he said, at <PERSON>Johnny Rush</PERSON>'s over the way there
and drive out the three of us together of a Sunday evening. He had his
mind set on that.... Poor <PERSON>James</PERSON>!"

"The Lord have mercy on his soul!" said my aunt.

<PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> took out her handkerchief and wiped her eyes with it. Then she put
it back again in her pocket and gazed into the empty grate for some time
without speaking.

"He was too scrupulous always," she said. "The duties of the priesthood
was too much for him. And then his life was, you might say, crossed."

"Yes," said my aunt. "He was a disappointed man. You could see that."

A silence took possession of the little room and, under cover of it, I
approached the table and tasted my sherry and then returned quietly to
my chair in the corner. <PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> seemed to have fallen into a deep revery.
We waited respectfully for her to break the silence: and after a long
pause she said slowly:

"It was that chalice he broke.... That was the beginning of it. Of
course, they say it was all right, that it contained nothing, I mean.
But still.... They say it was the boy's fault. But poor <PERSON>James</PERSON> was so
nervous, God be merciful to him!"

"And was that it?" said my aunt. "I heard something...."

<PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> nodded.

"That affected his mind," she said. "After that he began to mope by
himself, talking to no one and wandering about by himself. So one night
he was wanted for to go on a call and they couldn't find him anywhere.
They looked high up and low down; and still they couldn't see a sight
of him anywhere. So then the clerk suggested to try the chapel. So
then they got the keys and opened the chapel and the clerk and Father
<PERSON>O'Rourke</PERSON> and another priest that was there brought in a light for to
look for him.... And what do you think but there he was, sitting up by
himself in the dark in his confession-box, wide-awake and laughing-like
softly to himself?"

She stopped suddenly as if to listen. I too listened; but there was no
sound in the house: and I knew that the old priest was lying still in
his coffin as we had seen him, solemn and truculent in death, an idle
chalice on his breast.

<PERSON>Eliza</PERSON> resumed:

"Wide-awake and laughing-like to himself.... So then, of course, when
they saw that, that made them think that there was something gone wrong
with him...."



AN ENCOUNTER

IT was <PERSON>Joe Dillon</PERSON> who introduced the <LOCATION>Wild West</LOCATION> to us. He had a little
library made up of old numbers of _The Union <PERSON>Jack</PERSON>_, _Pluck_ and _The
Halfpenny Marvel_. Every evening after school we met in his back garden
and arranged Indian battles. He and his fat young brother <PERSON>Leo</PERSON>, the
idler, held the loft of the stable while we tried to carry it by storm;
or we fought a pitched battle on the grass. But, however well we fought,
we never won siege or battle and all our bouts ended with <PERSON>Joe Dillon</PERSON>'s
war dance of victory. His parents went to eight-o'clock mass every
morning in <LOCATION>Gardiner Street</LOCATION> and the peaceful odour of <PERSON>Mrs Dillon</PERSON> was
prevalent in the hall of the house. But he played too fiercely for us
who were younger and more timid. He looked like some kind of an Indian
when he capered round the garden, an old tea-cosy on his head, beating a
tin with his fist and yelling:

"Ya! yaka, yaka, yaka!"

Everyone was incredulous when it was reported that he had a vocation for
the priesthood. Nevertheless it was true.

A spirit of unruliness diffused itself among us and, under its
influence, differences of culture and constitution were waived. We
banded ourselves together, some boldly, some in jest and some almost in
fear: and of the number of these latter, the reluctant Indians who
were afraid to seem studious or lacking in robustness, I was one. The
adventures related in the literature of the <LOCATION>Wild West</LOCATION> were remote from
my nature but, at least, they opened doors of escape. I liked better
some American detective stories which were traversed from time to time
by unkempt fierce and beautiful girls. Though there was nothing wrong
in these stories and though their intention was sometimes literary
they were circulated secretly at school. One day when Father <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> was
hearing the four pages of Roman History clumsy <PERSON>Leo Dillon</PERSON> was discovered
with a copy of _The Halfpenny Marvel_.

"This page or this page? This page? Now, <PERSON>Dillon</PERSON>, up! _'Hardly had the
day'...._ Go on! What day? _'Hardly had the day dawned'...._ Have you
studied it? What have you there in your pocket?"

Everyone's heart palpitated as <PERSON>Leo Dillon</PERSON> handed up the paper and
everyone assumed an innocent face. Father <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> turned over the pages,
frowning.

"What is this rubbish?" he said. "_The Apache Chief!_ Is this what you
read instead of studying your Roman History? Let me not find any more
of this wretched stuff in this college. The man who wrote it, I suppose,
was some wretched fellow who writes these things for a drink. I'm
surprised at boys like you, educated, reading such stuff. I could
understand it if you were ... National School boys. Now, <PERSON>Dillon</PERSON>, I
advise you strongly, get at your work or...."

This rebuke during the sober hours of school paled much of the glory of
the <LOCATION>Wild West</LOCATION> for me and the confused puffy face of <PERSON>Leo Dillon</PERSON> awakened
one of my consciences. But when the restraining influence of the school
was at a distance I began to hunger again for wild sensations, for the
escape which those chronicles of disorder alone seemed to offer me. The
mimic warfare of the evening became at last as wearisome to me as the
routine of school in the morning because I wanted real adventures to
happen to myself. But real adventures, I reflected, do not happen to
people who remain at home: they must be sought abroad.

The summer holidays were near at hand when I made up my mind to break
out of the weariness of school-life for one day at least. With <PERSON>Leo
Dillon</PERSON> and a boy named <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> I planned a day's miching. Each of us
saved up sixpence. We were to meet at ten in the morning on the <LOCATION>Canal
Bridge</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>'s big sister was to write an excuse for him and <PERSON>Leo
Dillon</PERSON> was to tell his brother to say he was sick. We arranged to go
along the <LOCATION>Wharf Road</LOCATION> until we came to the ships, then to cross in the
ferryboat and walk out to see the <ORGANIZATION>Pigeon House</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Leo Dillon</PERSON> was afraid
we might meet Father <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> or someone out of the college; but <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>
asked, very sensibly, what would Father <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> be doing out at the
<ORGANIZATION>Pigeon House</ORGANIZATION>. We were reassured: and I brought the first stage of the
plot to an end by collecting sixpence from the other two, at the
same time showing them my own sixpence. When we were making the last
arrangements on the eve we were all vaguely excited. We shook hands,
laughing, and <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> said:

"Till tomorrow, mates!"

That night I slept badly. In the morning I was first-comer to the bridge
as I lived nearest. I hid my books in the long grass near the ashpit at
the end of the garden where nobody ever came and hurried along the canal
bank. It was a mild sunny morning in the first week of June. I sat up
on the coping of the bridge admiring my frail canvas shoes which I had
diligently pipeclayed overnight and watching the docile horses pulling
a tramload of business people up the hill. All the branches of the tall
trees which lined the mall were gay with little light green leaves and
the sunlight slanted through them on to the water. The granite stone of
the bridge was beginning to be warm and I began to pat it with my hands
in time to an air in my head. I was very happy.

When I had been sitting there for five or ten minutes I saw <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>'s
grey suit approaching. He came up the hill, smiling, and clambered
up beside me on the bridge. While we were waiting he brought out
the catapult which bulged from his inner pocket and explained some
improvements which he had made in it. I asked him why he had brought it
and he told me he had brought it to have some gas with the birds. <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>
used slang freely, and spoke of Father <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> as Old Bunser. We waited
on for a quarter of an hour more but still there was no sign of <PERSON>Leo
Dillon</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>, at last, jumped down and said:

"Come along. I knew Fatty'd funk it."

"And his sixpence...?" I said.

"That's forfeit," said <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>. "And so much the better for us--a bob and
a tanner instead of a bob."

We walked along the <LOCATION>North Strand Road</LOCATION> till we came to the Vitriol Works
and then turned to the right along the <LOCATION>Wharf Road</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> began to play
the Indian as soon as we were out of public sight. He chased a crowd
of ragged girls, brandishing his unloaded catapult and, when two ragged
boys began, out of chivalry, to fling stones at us, he proposed that we
should charge them. I objected that the boys were too small and so
we walked on, the ragged troop screaming after us: _"Swaddlers!
Swaddlers!"_ thinking that we were Protestants because <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>, who was
dark-complexioned, wore the silver badge of a cricket club in his cap.
When we came to the Smoothing Iron we arranged a siege; but it was a
failure because you must have at least three. We revenged ourselves on
<PERSON>Leo Dillon</PERSON> by saying what a funk he was and guessing how many he would
get at three o'clock from Mr <PERSON>Ryan</PERSON>.

We came then near the river. We spent a long time walking about the
noisy streets flanked by high stone walls, watching the working of
cranes and engines and often being shouted at for our immobility by the
drivers of groaning carts. It was noon when we reached the quays and, as
all the labourers seemed to be eating their lunches, we bought two big
currant buns and sat down to eat them on some metal piping beside the
river. We pleased ourselves with the spectacle of <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>'s commerce--the
barges signalled from far away by their curls of woolly smoke, the brown
fishing fleet beyond <LOCATION>Ringsend</LOCATION>, the big white sailing-vessel which was
being discharged on the opposite quay. <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> said it would be right
skit to run away to sea on one of those big ships and even I, looking at
the high masts, saw, or imagined, the geography which had been scantily
dosed to me at school gradually taking substance under my eyes. School
and home seemed to recede from us and their influences upon us seemed to
wane.

We crossed the <LOCATION>Liffey</LOCATION> in the ferryboat, paying our toll to be
transported in the company of two labourers and a little Jew with a bag.
We were serious to the point of solemnity, but once during the short
voyage our eyes met and we laughed. When we landed we watched the
discharging of the graceful threemaster which we had observed from the
other quay. Some bystander said that she was a Norwegian vessel. I went
to the stern and tried to decipher the legend upon it but, failing to do
so, I came back and examined the foreign sailors to see had any of them
green eyes for I had some confused notion.... The sailors' eyes were
blue and grey and even black. The only sailor whose eyes could have been
called green was a tall man who amused the crowd on the quay by calling
out cheerfully every time the planks fell:

"All right! All right!"

When we were tired of this sight we wandered slowly into Ringsend. The
day had grown sultry, and in the windows of the grocers' shops musty
biscuits lay bleaching. We bought some biscuits and chocolate which
we ate sedulously as we wandered through the squalid streets where the
families of the fishermen live. We could find no dairy and so we went
into a huckster's shop and bought a bottle of raspberry lemonade each.
Refreshed by this, <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> chased a cat down a lane, but the cat escaped
into a wide field. We both felt rather tired and when we reached the
field we made at once for a sloping bank over the ridge of which we
could see the Dodder.

It was too late and we were too tired to carry out our project of
visiting the <ORGANIZATION>Pigeon House</ORGANIZATION>. We had to be home before four o'clock lest
our adventure should be discovered. <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> looked regretfully at his
catapult and I had to suggest going home by train before he regained
any cheerfulness. The sun went in behind some clouds and left us to our
jaded thoughts and the crumbs of our provisions.

There was nobody but ourselves in the field. When we had lain on the
bank for some time without speaking I saw a man approaching from the far
end of the field. I watched him lazily as I chewed one of those green
stems on which girls tell fortunes. He came along by the bank slowly. He
walked with one hand upon his hip and in the other hand he held a stick
with which he tapped the turf lightly. He was shabbily dressed in a suit
of greenish-black and wore what we used to call a jerry hat with a high
crown. He seemed to be fairly old for his moustache was ashen-grey. When
he passed at our feet he glanced up at us quickly and then continued his
way. We followed him with our eyes and saw that when he had gone on for
perhaps fifty paces he turned about and began to retrace his steps. He
walked towards us very slowly, always tapping the ground with his stick,
so slowly that I thought he was looking for something in the grass.

He stopped when he came level with us and bade us good-day. We answered
him and he sat down beside us on the slope slowly and with great care.
He began to talk of the weather, saying that it would be a very hot
summer and adding that the seasons had changed greatly since he was a
boy--a long time ago. He said that the happiest time of one's life was
undoubtedly one's school-boy days and that he would give anything to be
young again. While he expressed these sentiments which bored us a little
we kept silent. Then he began to talk of school and of books. He asked
us whether we had read the poetry of <PERSON>Thomas Moore</PERSON> or the works of Sir
<PERSON>Walter Scott</PERSON> and Lord <PERSON>Lytton</PERSON>. I pretended that I had read every book he
mentioned so that in the end he said:

"Ah, I can see you are a bookworm like myself. Now," he added, pointing
to <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> who was regarding us with open eyes, "he is different; he goes
in for games."

He said he had all Sir <PERSON>Walter Scott</PERSON>'s works and all Lord <PERSON>Lytton</PERSON>'s works
at home and never tired of reading them. "Of course," he said, "there
were some of Lord <PERSON>Lytton</PERSON>'s works which boys couldn't read." <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> asked
why couldn't boys read them--a question which agitated and pained me
because I was afraid the man would think I was as stupid as <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>. The
man, however, only smiled. I saw that he had great gaps in his mouth
between his yellow teeth. Then he asked us which of us had the most
sweethearts. <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> mentioned lightly that he had three totties. The man
asked me how many had I. I answered that I had none. He did not believe
me and said he was sure I must have one. I was silent.

"Tell us," said <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> pertly to the man, "how many have you yourself?"

The man smiled as before and said that when he was our age he had lots
of sweethearts.

"Every boy," he said, "has a little sweetheart."

His attitude on this point struck me as strangely liberal in a man
of his age. In my heart I thought that what he said about boys and
sweethearts was reasonable. But I disliked the words in his mouth and I
wondered why he shivered once or twice as if he feared something or felt
a sudden chill. As he proceeded I noticed that his accent was good. He
began to speak to us about girls, saying what nice soft hair they had
and how soft their hands were and how all girls were not so good as they
seemed to be if one only knew. There was nothing he liked, he said, so
much as looking at a nice young girl, at her nice white hands and her
beautiful soft hair. He gave me the impression that he was repeating
something which he had learned by heart or that, magnetised by some
words of his own speech, his mind was slowly circling round and round in
the same orbit. At times he spoke as if he were simply alluding to some
fact that everybody knew, and at times he lowered his voice and spoke
mysteriously as if he were telling us something secret which he did not
wish others to overhear. He repeated his phrases over and over again,
varying them and surrounding them with his monotonous voice. I continued
to gaze towards the foot of the slope, listening to him.

After a long while his monologue paused. He stood up slowly, saying
that he had to leave us for a minute or so, a few minutes, and, without
changing the direction of my gaze, I saw him walking slowly away from us
towards the near end of the field. We remained silent when he had gone.
After a silence of a few minutes I heard <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> exclaim:

"I say! Look what he's doing!"

As I neither answered nor raised my eyes <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> exclaimed again:

"I say.... He's a queer old josser!"

"In case he asks us for our names," I said, "let you be <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON> and I'll
be <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>."

We said nothing further to each other. I was still considering whether
I would go away or not when the man came back and sat down beside us
again. Hardly had he sat down when <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON>, catching sight of the cat
which had escaped him, sprang up and pursued her across the field. The
man and I watched the chase. The cat escaped once more and <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> began
to throw stones at the wall she had escaladed. Desisting from this, he
began to wander about the far end of the field, aimlessly.

After an interval the man spoke to me. He said that my friend was a very
rough boy and asked did he get whipped often at school. I was going to
reply indignantly that we were not National School boys to be whipped,
as he called it; but I remained silent. He began to speak on the subject
of chastising boys. His mind, as if magnetised again by his speech,
seemed to circle slowly round and round its new centre. He said that
when boys were that kind they ought to be whipped and well whipped. When
a boy was rough and unruly there was nothing would do him any good but a
good sound whipping. A slap on the hand or a box on the ear was no good:
what he wanted was to get a nice warm whipping. I was surprised at this
sentiment and involuntarily glanced up at his face. As I did so I met
the gaze of a pair of bottle-green eyes peering at me from under a
twitching forehead. I turned my eyes away again.

The man continued his monologue. He seemed to have forgotten his recent
liberalism. He said that if ever he found a boy talking to girls or
having a girl for a sweetheart he would whip him and whip him; and that
would teach him not to be talking to girls. And if a boy had a girl
for a sweetheart and told lies about it then he would give him such
a whipping as no boy ever got in this world. He said that there was
nothing in this world he would like so well as that. He described to
me how he would whip such a boy as if he were unfolding some elaborate
mystery. He would love that, he said, better than anything in this
world; and his voice, as he led me monotonously through the mystery,
grew almost affectionate and seemed to plead with me that I should
understand him.

I waited till his monologue paused again. Then I stood up abruptly. Lest
I should betray my agitation I delayed a few moments pretending to fix
my shoe properly and then, saying that I was obliged to go, I bade him
good-day. I went up the slope calmly but my heart was beating quickly
with fear that he would seize me by the ankles. When I reached the top
of the slope I turned round and, without looking at him, called loudly
across the field:

"Murphy!"

My voice had an accent of forced bravery in it and I was ashamed of my
paltry stratagem. I had to call the name again before <PERSON>Mahony</PERSON> saw me
and hallooed in answer. How my heart beat as he came running across the
field to me! He ran as if to bring me aid. And I was penitent; for in my
heart I had always despised him a little.



ARABY

NORTH RICHMOND STREET, being blind, was a quiet street except at
the hour when the <ORGANIZATION>Christian Brothers' School</ORGANIZATION> set the boys free. An
uninhabited house of two storeys stood at the blind end, detached from
its neighbours in a square ground. The other houses of the street,
conscious of decent lives within them, gazed at one another with brown
imperturbable faces.

The former tenant of our house, a priest, had died in the back
drawing-room. Air, musty from having been long enclosed, hung in all
the rooms, and the waste room behind the kitchen was littered with old
useless papers. Among these I found a few paper-covered books, the pages
of which were curled and damp: _The Abbot_, by <PERSON>Walter Scott</PERSON>, _The Devout
Communicant_ and _The Memoirs of <LOCATION>Vidocq</LOCATION>_. I liked the last best because
its leaves were yellow. The wild garden behind the house contained a
central apple-tree and a few straggling bushes under one of which
I found the late tenant's rusty bicycle-pump. He had been a very
charitable priest; in his will he had left all his money to institutions
and the furniture of his house to his sister.

When the short days of winter came dusk fell before we had well eaten
our dinners. When we met in the street the houses had grown sombre. The
space of sky above us was the colour of ever-changing violet and towards
it the lamps of the street lifted their feeble lanterns. The cold air
stung us and we played till our bodies glowed. Our shouts echoed in the
silent street. The career of our play brought us through the dark muddy
lanes behind the houses where we ran the gauntlet of the rough tribes
from the cottages, to the back doors of the dark dripping gardens where
odours arose from the ashpits, to the dark odorous stables where a
coachman smoothed and combed the horse or shook music from the buckled
harness. When we returned to the street light from the kitchen windows
had filled the areas. If my uncle was seen turning the corner we hid in
the shadow until we had seen him safely housed. Or if <PERSON>Mangan</PERSON>'s sister
came out on the doorstep to call her brother in to his tea we watched
her from our shadow peer up and down the street. We waited to see
whether she would remain or go in and, if she remained, we left our
shadow and walked up to <PERSON>Mangan</PERSON>'s steps resignedly. She was waiting
for us, her figure defined by the light from the half-opened door. Her
brother always teased her before he obeyed and I stood by the railings
looking at her. Her dress swung as she moved her body and the soft rope
of her hair tossed from side to side.

Every morning I lay on the floor in the front parlour watching her door.
The blind was pulled down to within an inch of the sash so that I could
not be seen. When she came out on the doorstep my heart leaped. I ran
to the hall, seized my books and followed her. I kept her brown figure
always in my eye and, when we came near the point at which our ways
diverged, I quickened my pace and passed her. This happened morning
after morning. I had never spoken to her, except for a few casual words,
and yet her name was like a summons to all my foolish blood.

Her image accompanied me even in places the most hostile to romance. On
Saturday evenings when my aunt went marketing I had to go to carry
some of the parcels. We walked through the flaring streets, jostled
by drunken men and bargaining women, amid the curses of labourers, the
shrill litanies of shop-boys who stood on guard by the barrels of pigs'
cheeks, the nasal chanting of street-singers, who sang a _come-all-you_
about <PERSON>O'Donovan Rossa</PERSON>, or a ballad about the troubles in our native
land. These noises converged in a single sensation of life for me: I
imagined that I bore my chalice safely through a throng of foes. Her
name sprang to my lips at moments in strange prayers and praises which I
myself did not understand. My eyes were often full of tears (I could not
tell why) and at times a flood from my heart seemed to pour itself out
into my bosom. I thought little of the future. I did not know whether I
would ever speak to her or not or, if I spoke to her, how I could tell
her of my confused adoration. But my body was like a harp and her words
and gestures were like fingers running upon the wires.

One evening I went into the back drawing-room in which the priest had
died. It was a dark rainy evening and there was no sound in the house.
Through one of the broken panes I heard the rain impinge upon the earth,
the fine incessant needles of water playing in the sodden beds. Some
distant lamp or lighted window gleamed below me. I was thankful that I
could see so little. All my senses seemed to desire to veil themselves
and, feeling that I was about to slip from them, I pressed the palms of
my hands together until they trembled, murmuring: _"O love! O love!"_
many times.

At last she spoke to me. When she addressed the first words to me I was
so confused that I did not know what to answer. She asked me was I
going to _Araby_. I forgot whether I answered yes or no. It would be a
splendid bazaar, she said; she would love to go.

"And why can't you?" I asked.

While she spoke she turned a silver bracelet round and round her wrist.
She could not go, she said, because there would be a retreat that week
in her convent. Her brother and two other boys were fighting for their
caps and I was alone at the railings. She held one of the spikes, bowing
her head towards me. The light from the lamp opposite our door caught
the white curve of her neck, lit up her hair that rested there and,
falling, lit up the hand upon the railing. It fell over one side of her
dress and caught the white border of a petticoat, just visible as she
stood at ease.

"It's well for you," she said.

"If I go," I said, "I will bring you something."

What innumerable follies laid waste my waking and sleeping thoughts
after that evening! I wished to annihilate the tedious intervening days.
I chafed against the work of school. At night in my bedroom and by day
in the classroom her image came between me and the page I strove to
read. The syllables of the word _Araby_ were called to me through the
silence in which my soul luxuriated and cast an Eastern enchantment over
me. I asked for leave to go to the bazaar on Saturday night. My aunt
was surprised and hoped it was not some Freemason affair. I answered few
questions in class. I watched my master's face pass from amiability to
sternness; he hoped I was not beginning to idle. I could not call my
wandering thoughts together. I had hardly any patience with the serious
work of life which, now that it stood between me and my desire, seemed
to me child's play, ugly monotonous child's play.

On Saturday morning I reminded my uncle that I wished to go to the
bazaar in the evening. He was fussing at the hallstand, looking for the
hat-brush, and answered me curtly:

"Yes, boy, I know."

As he was in the hall I could not go into the front parlour and lie at
the window. I left the house in bad humour and walked slowly towards the
school. The air was pitilessly raw and already my heart misgave me.

When I came home to dinner my uncle had not yet been home. Still it was
early. I sat staring at the clock for some time and, when its ticking
began to irritate me, I left the room. I mounted the staircase and
gained the upper part of the house. The high cold empty gloomy rooms
liberated me and I went from room to room singing. From the front window
I saw my companions playing below in the street. Their cries reached me
weakened and indistinct and, leaning my forehead against the cool glass,
I looked over at the dark house where she lived. I may have stood
there for an hour, seeing nothing but the brown-clad figure cast by my
imagination, touched discreetly by the lamplight at the curved neck, at
the hand upon the railings and at the border below the dress.

When I came downstairs again I found <PERSON>Mrs Mercer</PERSON> sitting at the fire.
She was an old garrulous woman, a pawnbroker's widow, who collected
used stamps for some pious purpose. I had to endure the gossip of the
tea-table. The meal was prolonged beyond an hour and still my uncle did
not come. <PERSON>Mrs Mercer</PERSON> stood up to go: she was sorry she couldn't wait any
longer, but it was after eight o'clock and she did not like to be out
late as the night air was bad for her. When she had gone I began to walk
up and down the room, clenching my fists. My aunt said:

"I'm afraid you may put off your bazaar for this night of Our Lord."

At nine o'clock I heard my uncle's latchkey in the halldoor. I heard him
talking to himself and heard the hallstand rocking when it had received
the weight of his overcoat. I could interpret these signs. When he was
midway through his dinner I asked him to give me the money to go to the
bazaar. He had forgotten.

"The people are in bed and after their first sleep now," he said.

I did not smile. My aunt said to him energetically:

"Can't you give him the money and let him go? You've kept him late
enough as it is."

My uncle said he was very sorry he had forgotten. He said he believed in
the old saying: "All work and no play makes <PERSON>Jack</PERSON> a dull boy." He asked
me where I was going and, when I had told him a second time he asked me
did I know _The Arab's Farewell to his Steed_. When I left the kitchen
he was about to recite the opening lines of the piece to my aunt.

I held a florin tightly in my hand as I strode down <LOCATION>Buckingham Street</LOCATION>
towards the station. The sight of the streets thronged with buyers and
glaring with gas recalled to me the purpose of my journey. I took my
seat in a third-class carriage of a deserted train. After an intolerable
delay the train moved out of the station slowly. It crept onward among
ruinous houses and over the twinkling river. At <LOCATION>Westland Row Station</LOCATION>
a crowd of people pressed to the carriage doors; but the porters moved
them back, saying that it was a special train for the bazaar. I remained
alone in the bare carriage. In a few minutes the train drew up beside an
improvised wooden platform. I passed out on to the road and saw by the
lighted dial of a clock that it was ten minutes to ten. In front of me
was a large building which displayed the magical name.

I could not find any sixpenny entrance and, fearing that the bazaar
would be closed, I passed in quickly through a turnstile, handing a
shilling to a weary-looking man. I found myself in a big hall girdled at
half its height by a gallery. Nearly all the stalls were closed and the
greater part of the hall was in darkness. I recognised a silence like
that which pervades a church after a service. I walked into the centre
of the bazaar timidly. A few people were gathered about the stalls which
were still open. Before a curtain, over which the words _Café Chantant_
were written in coloured lamps, two men were counting money on a salver.
I listened to the fall of the coins.

Remembering with difficulty why I had come I went over to one of the
stalls and examined porcelain vases and flowered tea-sets. At the
door of the stall a young lady was talking and laughing with two young
gentlemen. I remarked their English accents and listened vaguely to
their conversation.

"O, I never said such a thing!"

"O, but you did!"

"O, but I didn't!"

"Didn't she say that?"

"Yes. I heard her."

"O, there's a ... fib!"

Observing me the young lady came over and asked me did I wish to buy
anything. The tone of her voice was not encouraging; she seemed to have
spoken to me out of a sense of duty. I looked humbly at the great jars
that stood like eastern guards at either side of the dark entrance to
the stall and murmured:

"No, thank you."

The young lady changed the position of one of the vases and went back to
the two young men. They began to talk of the same subject. Once or twice
the young lady glanced at me over her shoulder.

I lingered before her stall, though I knew my stay was useless, to make
my interest in her wares seem the more real. Then I turned away slowly
and walked down the middle of the bazaar. I allowed the two pennies to
fall against the sixpence in my pocket. I heard a voice call from one
end of the gallery that the light was out. The upper part of the hall
was now completely dark.

Gazing up into the darkness I saw myself as a creature driven and
derided by vanity; and my eyes burned with anguish and anger.



<PERSON>EVELINE</PERSON>

SHE sat at the window watching the evening invade the avenue. Her head
was leaned against the window curtains and in her nostrils was the odour
of dusty cretonne. She was tired.

Few people passed. The man out of the last house passed on his way
home; she heard his footsteps clacking along the concrete pavement and
afterwards crunching on the cinder path before the new red houses. One
time there used to be a field there in which they used to play every
evening with other people's children. Then a man from <LOCATION>Belfast</LOCATION> bought
the field and built houses in it--not like their little brown houses but
bright brick houses with shining roofs. The children of the avenue used
to play together in that field--the <LOCATION>Devines</LOCATION>, the Waters, the <ORGANIZATION>Dunns</ORGANIZATION>,
little <PERSON>Keogh</PERSON> the cripple, she and her brothers and sisters. <PERSON>Ernest</PERSON>,
however, never played: he was too grown up. Her father used often to
hunt them in out of the field with his blackthorn stick; but usually
little <PERSON>Keogh</PERSON> used to keep _nix_ and call out when he saw her father
coming. Still they seemed to have been rather happy then. Her father was
not so bad then; and besides, her mother was alive. That was a long time
ago; she and her brothers and sisters were all grown up; her mother
was dead. <PERSON>Tizzie Dunn</PERSON> was dead, too, and the Waters had gone back to
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. Everything changes. Now she was going to go away like the
others, to leave her home.

Home! She looked round the room, reviewing all its familiar objects
which she had dusted once a week for so many years, wondering where on
earth all the dust came from. Perhaps she would never see again those
familiar objects from which she had never dreamed of being divided.
And yet during all those years she had never found out the name of the
priest whose yellowing photograph hung on the wall above the broken
harmonium beside the coloured print of the promises made to Blessed
<PERSON>Margaret Mary Alacoque</PERSON>. He had been a school friend of her father.
Whenever he showed the photograph to a visitor her father used to pass
it with a casual word:

"He is in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> now."

She had consented to go away, to leave her home. Was that wise? She
tried to weigh each side of the question. In her home anyway she had
shelter and food; she had those whom she had known all her life about
her. Of course she had to work hard, both in the house and at business.
What would they say of her in the Stores when they found out that she
had run away with a fellow? Say she was a fool, perhaps; and her place
would be filled up by advertisement. Miss <PERSON>Gavan</PERSON> would be glad. She
had always had an edge on her, especially whenever there were people
listening.

"Miss <PERSON>Hill</PERSON>, don't you see these ladies are waiting?"

"Look lively, <LOCATION>Miss Hill</LOCATION>, please."

She would not cry many tears at leaving the Stores.

But in her new home, in a distant unknown country, it would not be like
that. Then she would be married--she, <PERSON>Eveline</PERSON>. People would treat her
with respect then. She would not be treated as her mother had been. Even
now, though she was over nineteen, she sometimes felt herself in danger
of her father's violence. She knew it was that that had given her the
palpitations. When they were growing up he had never gone for her like
he used to go for <PERSON>Harry</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ernest</PERSON>, because she was a girl; but latterly
he had begun to threaten her and say what he would do to her only for
her dead mother's sake. And now she had nobody to protect her. <PERSON>Ernest</PERSON>
was dead and <PERSON>Harry</PERSON>, who was in the church decorating business, was
nearly always down somewhere in the country. Besides, the invariable
squabble for money on Saturday nights had begun to weary her
unspeakably. She always gave her entire wages--seven shillings--and
<PERSON>Harry</PERSON> always sent up what he could but the trouble was to get any money
from her father. He said she used to squander the money, that she had
no head, that he wasn't going to give her his hard-earned money to throw
about the streets, and much more, for he was usually fairly bad of a
Saturday night. In the end he would give her the money and ask her had
she any intention of buying Sunday's dinner. Then she had to rush out
as quickly as she could and do her marketing, holding her black leather
purse tightly in her hand as she elbowed her way through the crowds and
returning home late under her load of provisions. She had hard work to
keep the house together and to see that the two young children who had
been left to her charge went to school regularly and got their meals
regularly. It was hard work--a hard life--but now that she was about to
leave it she did not find it a wholly undesirable life.

She was about to explore another life with <PERSON>Frank</PERSON>. <PERSON>Frank</PERSON> was very kind,
manly, open-hearted. She was to go away with him by the night-boat to
be his wife and to live with him in <LOCATION>Buenos Ayres</LOCATION> where he had a home
waiting for her. How well she remembered the first time she had seen
him; he was lodging in a house on the main road where she used to visit.
It seemed a few weeks ago. He was standing at the gate, his peaked cap
pushed back on his head and his hair tumbled forward over a face of
bronze. Then they had come to know each other. He used to meet her
outside the Stores every evening and see her home. He took her to see
_The Bohemian Girl_ and she felt elated as she sat in an unaccustomed
part of the theatre with him. He was awfully fond of music and sang a
little. People knew that they were courting and, when he sang about the
lass that loves a sailor, she always felt pleasantly confused. He used
to call her Poppens out of fun. First of all it had been an excitement
for her to have a fellow and then she had begun to like him. He had
tales of distant countries. He had started as a deck boy at a pound a
month on a ship of the Allan Line going out to <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. He told her
the names of the ships he had been on and the names of the different
services. He had sailed through the Straits of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> and he told her
stories of the terrible Patagonians. He had fallen on his feet in <PERSON>Buenos
Ayres</PERSON>, he said, and had come over to the old country just for a holiday.
Of course, her father had found out the affair and had forbidden her to
have anything to say to him.

"I know these sailor chaps," he said.

One day he had quarrelled with <PERSON>Frank</PERSON> and after that she had to meet her
lover secretly.

The evening deepened in the avenue. The white of two letters in her lap
grew indistinct. One was to <PERSON>Harry</PERSON>; the other was to her father. <PERSON>Ernest</PERSON>
had been her favourite but she liked <PERSON>Harry</PERSON> too. Her father was becoming
old lately, she noticed; he would miss her. Sometimes he could be very
nice. Not long before, when she had been laid up for a day, he had read
her out a ghost story and made toast for her at the fire. Another day,
when their mother was alive, they had all gone for a picnic to the Hill
of <LOCATION>Howth</LOCATION>. She remembered her father putting on her mother's bonnet to
make the children laugh.

Her time was running out but she continued to sit by the window,
leaning her head against the window curtain, inhaling the odour of dusty
cretonne. Down far in the avenue she could hear a street organ playing.
She knew the air. Strange that it should come that very night to remind
her of the promise to her mother, her promise to keep the home together
as long as she could. She remembered the last night of her mother's
illness; she was again in the close dark room at the other side of the
hall and outside she heard a melancholy air of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. The organ-player
had been ordered to go away and given sixpence. She remembered her
father strutting back into the sickroom saying:

"Damned Italians! coming over here!"

As she mused the pitiful vision of her mother's life laid its spell on
the very quick of her being--that life of commonplace sacrifices closing
in final craziness. She trembled as she heard again her mother's voice
saying constantly with foolish insistence:

"Derevaun Seraun! <PERSON>Derevaun Seraun</PERSON>!"

She stood up in a sudden impulse of terror. Escape! She must escape!
Frank would save her. He would give her life, perhaps love, too. But she
wanted to live. Why should she be unhappy? She had a right to happiness.
Frank would take her in his arms, fold her in his arms. He would save
her.



She stood among the swaying crowd in the station at the <LOCATION>North Wall</LOCATION>. He
held her hand and she knew that he was speaking to her, saying something
about the passage over and over again. The station was full of soldiers
with brown baggages. Through the wide doors of the sheds she caught a
glimpse of the black mass of the boat, lying in beside the quay wall,
with illumined portholes. She answered nothing. She felt her cheek pale
and cold and, out of a maze of distress, she prayed to God to direct
her, to show her what was her duty. The boat blew a long mournful
whistle into the mist. If she went, tomorrow she would be on the sea
with Frank, steaming towards <PERSON>Buenos Ayres</PERSON>. Their passage had been
booked. Could she still draw back after all he had done for her? Her
distress awoke a nausea in her body and she kept moving her lips in
silent fervent prayer.

A bell clanged upon her heart. She felt him seize her hand:

"Come!"

All the seas of the world tumbled about her heart. He was drawing her
into them: he would drown her. She gripped with both hands at the iron
railing.

"Come!"

No! No! No! It was impossible. Her hands clutched the iron in frenzy.
Amid the seas she sent a cry of anguish!

"Eveline! Evvy!"

He rushed beyond the barrier and called to her to follow. He was shouted
at to go on but he still called to her. She set her white face to him,
passive, like a helpless animal. Her eyes gave him no sign of love or
farewell or recognition.



AFTER THE RACE

THE cars came scudding in towards <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, running evenly like pellets
in the groove of the <LOCATION>Naas Road</LOCATION>. At the crest of the hill at <LOCATION>Inchicore</LOCATION>
sightseers had gathered in clumps to watch the cars careering homeward
and through this channel of poverty and inaction the Continent sped its
wealth and industry. Now and again the clumps of people raised the cheer
of the gratefully oppressed. Their sympathy, however, was for the blue
cars--the cars of their friends, the French.

The French, moreover, were virtual victors. Their team had finished
solidly; they had been placed second and third and the driver of the
winning German car was reported a Belgian. Each blue car, therefore,
received a double measure of welcome as it topped the crest of the hill
and each cheer of welcome was acknowledged with smiles and nods by those
in the car. In one of these trimly built cars was a party of four
young men whose spirits seemed to be at present well above the level
of successful Gallicism: in fact, these four young men were almost
hilarious. They were <PERSON>Charles Ségouin</PERSON>, the owner of the car; <PERSON>André
Rivière</PERSON>, a young electrician of Canadian birth; a huge Hungarian named
<PERSON>Villona</PERSON> and a neatly groomed young man named <PERSON>Doyle</PERSON>. <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON> was in good
humour because he had unexpectedly received some orders in advance (he
was about to start a motor establishment in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>) and <PERSON>Rivière</PERSON> was in
good humour because he was to be appointed manager of the establishment;
these two young men (who were cousins) were also in good humour because
of the success of the French cars. <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> was in good humour because he
had had a very satisfactory luncheon; and besides he was an optimist by
nature. The fourth member of the party, however, was too excited to be
genuinely happy.

He was about twenty-six years of age, with a soft, light brown moustache
and rather innocent-looking grey eyes. His father, who had begun life as
an advanced Nationalist, had modified his views early. He had made his
money as a butcher in <LOCATION>Kingstown</LOCATION> and by opening shops in <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> and in
the suburbs he had made his money many times over. He had also been
fortunate enough to secure some of the police contracts and in the end
he had become rich enough to be alluded to in the <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> newspapers as a
merchant prince. He had sent his son to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> to be educated in a big
<PERSON>Catholic</PERSON> college and had afterwards sent him to <ORGANIZATION>Dublin University</ORGANIZATION> to
study law. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> did not study very earnestly and took to bad courses
for a while. He had money and he was popular; and he divided his time
curiously between musical and motoring circles. Then he had been sent
for a term to <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> to see a little life. His father, remonstrative,
but covertly proud of the excess, had paid his bills and brought him
home. It was at <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> that he had met Ségouin. They were not much
more than acquaintances as yet but <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> found great pleasure in the
society of one who had seen so much of the world and was reputed to
own some of the biggest hotels in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. Such a person (as his father
agreed) was well worth knowing, even if he had not been the charming
companion he was. <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> was entertaining also--a brilliant
pianist--but, unfortunately, very poor.

The car ran on merrily with its cargo of hilarious youth. The two
cousins sat on the front seat; <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> and his Hungarian friend sat
behind. Decidedly <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> was in excellent spirits; he kept up a deep
bass hum of melody for miles of the road. The Frenchmen flung their
laughter and light words over their shoulders and often <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> had
to strain forward to catch the quick phrase. This was not altogether
pleasant for him, as he had nearly always to make a deft guess at the
meaning and shout back a suitable answer in the face of a high wind.
Besides <PERSON>Villona</PERSON>'s humming would confuse anybody; the noise of the car,
too.

Rapid motion through space elates one; so does notoriety; so does
the possession of money. These were three good reasons for <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>'s
excitement. He had been seen by many of his friends that day in the
company of these Continentals. At the control <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON> had presented him
to one of the French competitors and, in answer to his confused murmur
of compliment, the swarthy face of the driver had disclosed a line of
shining white teeth. It was pleasant after that honour to return to the
profane world of spectators amid nudges and significant looks. Then
as to money--he really had a great sum under his control. <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON>,
perhaps, would not think it a great sum but <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> who, in spite of
temporary errors, was at heart the inheritor of solid instincts knew
well with what difficulty it had been got together. This knowledge had
previously kept his bills within the limits of reasonable recklessness,
and, if he had been so conscious of the labour latent in money when
there had been question merely of some freak of the higher intelligence,
how much more so now when he was about to stake the greater part of his
substance! It was a serious thing for him.

Of course, the investment was a good one and <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON> had managed to
give the impression that it was by a favour of friendship the mite of
Irish money was to be included in the capital of the concern. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> had
a respect for his father's shrewdness in business matters and in this
case it had been his father who had first suggested the investment;
money to be made in the motor business, pots of money. Moreover <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON>
had the unmistakable air of wealth. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> set out to translate into
days' work that lordly car in which he sat. How smoothly it ran. In what
style they had come careering along the country roads! The journey
laid a magical finger on the genuine pulse of life and gallantly the
machinery of human nerves strove to answer the bounding courses of the
swift blue animal.

They drove down <LOCATION>Dame Street</LOCATION>. The street was busy with unusual
traffic, loud with the horns of motorists and the gongs of impatient
tram-drivers. Near the <ORGANIZATION>Bank Ségouin</ORGANIZATION> drew up and <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> and his friend
alighted. A little knot of people collected on the footpath to pay
homage to the snorting motor. The party was to dine together that
evening in <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON>'s hotel and, meanwhile, <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> and his friend, who
was staying with him, were to go home to dress. The car steered out
slowly for <LOCATION>Grafton Street</LOCATION> while the two young men pushed their way
through the knot of gazers. They walked northward with a curious feeling
of disappointment in the exercise, while the city hung its pale globes
of light above them in a haze of summer evening.

In <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>'s house this dinner had been pronounced an occasion. A certain
pride mingled with his parents' trepidation, a certain eagerness, also,
to play fast and loose for the names of great foreign cities have at
least this virtue. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>, too, looked very well when he was dressed and,
as he stood in the hall giving a last equation to the bows of his dress
tie, his father may have felt even commercially satisfied at having
secured for his son qualities often unpurchaseable. His father,
therefore, was unusually friendly with <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> and his manner expressed
a real respect for foreign accomplishments; but this subtlety of his
host was probably lost upon the Hungarian, who was beginning to have a
sharp desire for his dinner.

The dinner was excellent, exquisite. Ségouin, <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> decided, had a very
refined taste. The party was increased by a young Englishman named <PERSON>Routh</PERSON>
whom <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> had seen with <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON> at <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>. The young men supped in
a snug room lit by electric candle-lamps. They talked volubly and with
little reserve. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>, whose imagination was kindling, conceived the
lively youth of the Frenchmen twined elegantly upon the firm framework
of the Englishman's manner. A graceful image of his, he thought, and a
just one. He admired the dexterity with which their host directed the
conversation. The five young men had various tastes and their tongues
had been loosened. <PERSON>Villona</PERSON>, with immense respect, began to discover to
the mildly surprised Englishman the beauties of the English madrigal,
deploring the loss of old instruments. Rivière, not wholly ingenuously,
undertook to explain to <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> the triumph of the French mechanicians.
The resonant voice of the Hungarian was about to prevail in ridicule of
the spurious lutes of the romantic painters when <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON> shepherded
his party into politics. Here was congenial ground for all. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>, under
generous influences, felt the buried zeal of his father wake to life
within him: he aroused the torpid <PERSON>Routh</PERSON> at last. The room grew doubly
hot and <PERSON>Ségouin</PERSON>'s task grew harder each moment: there was even danger
of personal spite. The alert host at an opportunity lifted his glass
to Humanity and, when the toast had been drunk, he threw open a window
significantly.

That night the city wore the mask of a capital. The five young men
strolled along <PERSON>Stephen</PERSON>'s Green in a faint cloud of aromatic smoke. They
talked loudly and gaily and their cloaks dangled from their shoulders.
The people made way for them. At the corner of <LOCATION>Grafton Street</LOCATION> a short
fat man was putting two handsome ladies on a car in charge of another
fat man. The car drove off and the short fat man caught sight of the
party.

"André."

"It's <PERSON>Farley</PERSON>!"

A torrent of talk followed. <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> was an American. No one knew very
well what the talk was about. <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rivière</PERSON> were the noisiest,
but all the men were excited. They got up on a car, squeezing themselves
together amid much laughter. They drove by the crowd, blended now into
soft colours, to a music of merry bells. They took the train at <ORGANIZATION>Westland</ORGANIZATION>
Row and in a few seconds, as it seemed to <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>, they were walking out
of <LOCATION>Kingstown Station</LOCATION>. The ticket-collector saluted <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>; he was an old
man:

"Fine night, sir!"

It was a serene summer night; the harbour lay like a darkened mirror at
their feet. They proceeded towards it with linked arms, singing _Cadet
<PERSON>Roussel</PERSON>_ in chorus, stamping their feet at every:

_"Ho! Ho! Hohé, vraiment!"_

They got into a rowboat at the slip and made out for the American's
yacht. There was to be supper, music, cards. <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> said with
conviction:

"It is delightful!"

There was a yacht piano in the cabin. <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> played a waltz for <PERSON>Farley</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Rivière</PERSON>, <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> acting as cavalier and <PERSON>Rivière</PERSON> as lady. Then
an impromptu square dance, the men devising original figures. What
merriment! <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> took his part with a will; this was seeing life, at
least. Then <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> got out of breath and cried _"Stop!"_ A man brought
in a light supper, and the young men sat down to it for form's sake.
They drank, however: it was Bohemian. They drank <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>United States of America</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> made a speech, a
long speech, <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> saying: _"Hear! hear!"_ whenever there was a pause.
There was a great clapping of hands when he sat down. It must have been
a good speech. <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> clapped him on the back and laughed loudly. What
jovial fellows! What good company they were!

Cards! cards! The table was cleared. <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> returned quietly to his
piano and played voluntaries for them. The other men played game after
game, flinging themselves boldly into the adventure. They drank the
health of the <ORGANIZATION>Queen of Hearts</ORGANIZATION> and of the <ORGANIZATION>Queen of Diamonds</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> felt
obscurely the lack of an audience: the wit was flashing. Play ran very
high and paper began to pass. <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> did not know exactly who was
winning but he knew that he was losing. But it was his own fault for
he frequently mistook his cards and the other men had to calculate his
I.O.U.'s for him. They were devils of fellows but he wished they would
stop: it was getting late. Someone gave the toast of the yacht _The
<ORGANIZATION>Belle of Newport</ORGANIZATION>_ and then someone proposed one great game for a finish.

The piano had stopped; <PERSON>Villona</PERSON> must have gone up on deck. It was a
terrible game. They stopped just before the end of it to drink for luck.
<PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> understood that the game lay between <PERSON>Routh</PERSON> and Ségouin. What
excitement! <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> was excited too; he would lose, of course. How much
had he written away? The men rose to their feet to play the last tricks.
talking and gesticulating. <PERSON>Routh</PERSON> won. The cabin shook with the young
men's cheering and the cards were bundled together. They began then to
gather in what they had won. <PERSON>Farley</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> were the heaviest losers.

He knew that he would regret in the morning but at present he was glad
of the rest, glad of the dark stupor that would cover up his folly. He
leaned his elbows on the table and rested his head between his hands,
counting the beats of his temples. The cabin door opened and he saw the
Hungarian standing in a shaft of grey light:

"Daybreak, gentlemen!"



TWO GALLANTS

THE grey warm evening of August had descended upon the city and a mild
warm air, a memory of summer, circulated in the streets. The streets,
shuttered for the repose of Sunday, swarmed with a gaily coloured crowd.
Like illumined pearls the lamps shone from the summits of their tall
poles upon the living texture below which, changing shape and hue
unceasingly, sent up into the warm grey evening air an unchanging
unceasing murmur.

Two young men came down the hill of <LOCATION>Rutland Square</LOCATION>. One of them was just
bringing a long monologue to a close. The other, who walked on the verge
of the path and was at times obliged to step on to the road, owing to
his companion's rudeness, wore an amused listening face. He was squat
and ruddy. A yachting cap was shoved far back from his forehead and the
narrative to which he listened made constant waves of expression break
forth over his face from the corners of his nose and eyes and mouth.
Little jets of wheezing laughter followed one another out of his
convulsed body. His eyes, twinkling with cunning enjoyment, glanced at
every moment towards his companion's face. Once or twice he rearranged
the light waterproof which he had slung over one shoulder in toreador
fashion. His breeches, his white rubber shoes and his jauntily slung
waterproof expressed youth. But his figure fell into rotundity at the
waist, his hair was scant and grey and his face, when the waves of
expression had passed over it, had a ravaged look.

When he was quite sure that the narrative had ended he laughed
noiselessly for fully half a minute. Then he said:

"Well!... That takes the biscuit!"

His voice seemed winnowed of vigour; and to enforce his words he added
with humour:

"That takes the solitary, unique, and, if I may so call it, _recherché_
biscuit!"

He became serious and silent when he had said this. His tongue was tired
for he had been talking all the afternoon in a public-house in <LOCATION>Dorset
Street</LOCATION>. Most people considered <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> a leech but, in spite of this
reputation, his adroitness and eloquence had always prevented his
friends from forming any general policy against him. He had a brave
manner of coming up to a party of them in a bar and of holding himself
nimbly at the borders of the company until he was included in a round.
He was a sporting vagrant armed with a vast stock of stories, limericks
and riddles. He was insensitive to all kinds of discourtesy. No one
knew how he achieved the stern task of living, but his name was vaguely
associated with racing tissues.

"And where did you pick her up, <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>?" he asked.

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> ran his tongue swiftly along his upper lip.

"One night, man," he said, "I was going along Dame Street and I spotted
a fine tart under Waterhouse's clock and said good-night, you know. So
we went for a walk round by the canal and she told me she was a slavey
in a house in <LOCATION>Baggot Street</LOCATION>. I put my arm round her and squeezed her a
bit that night. Then next Sunday, man, I met her by appointment. We went
out to Donnybrook and I brought her into a field there. She told me she
used to go with a dairyman.... It was fine, man. Cigarettes every night
she'd bring me and paying the tram out and back. And one night she
brought me two bloody fine cigars--O, the real cheese, you know, that
the old fellow used to smoke.... I was afraid, man, she'd get in the
family way. But she's up to the dodge."

"Maybe she thinks you'll marry her," said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>.

"I told her I was out of a job," said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>. "I told her I was in
<LOCATION>Pim</LOCATION>'s. She doesn't know my name. I was too hairy to tell her that. But
she thinks I'm a bit of class, you know."

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> laughed again, noiselessly.

"Of all the good ones ever I heard," he said, "that emphatically takes
the biscuit."

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON>'s stride acknowledged the compliment. The swing of his burly body
made his friend execute a few light skips from the path to the roadway
and back again. <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> was the son of an inspector of police and he had
inherited his father's frame and gait. He walked with his hands by his
sides, holding himself erect and swaying his head from side to side. His
head was large, globular and oily; it sweated in all weathers; and his
large round hat, set upon it sideways, looked like a bulb which had
grown out of another. He always stared straight before him as if he were
on parade and, when he wished to gaze after someone in the street, it
was necessary for him to move his body from the hips. At present he was
about town. Whenever any job was vacant a friend was always ready to
give him the hard word. He was often to be seen walking with policemen
in plain clothes, talking earnestly. He knew the inner side of all
affairs and was fond of delivering final judgments. He spoke without
listening to the speech of his companions. His conversation was mainly
about himself: what he had said to such a person and what such a person
had said to him and what he had said to settle the matter. When he
reported these dialogues he aspirated the first letter of his name after
the manner of <LOCATION>Florentines</LOCATION>.

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> offered his friend a cigarette. As the two young men walked on
through the crowd <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> occasionally turned to smile at some of the
passing girls but <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>'s gaze was fixed on the large faint moon
circled with a double halo. He watched earnestly the passing of the grey
web of twilight across its face. At length he said:

"Well ... tell me, <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>, I suppose you'll be able to pull it off all
right, eh?"

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> closed one eye expressively as an answer.

"Is she game for that?" asked <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> dubiously. "You can never know
women."

"She's all right," said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>. "I know the way to get around her, man.
She's a bit gone on me."

"You're what I call a gay Lothario," said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>. "And the proper kind
of a Lothario, too!"

A shade of mockery relieved the servility of his manner. To save himself
he had the habit of leaving his flattery open to the interpretation of
raillery. But <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> had not a subtle mind.

"There's nothing to touch a good slavey," he affirmed. "Take my tip for
it."

"By one who has tried them all," said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>.

"First I used to go with girls, you know," said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>, unbosoming;
"girls off the <LOCATION>South Circular</LOCATION>. I used to take them out, man, on the
tram somewhere and pay the tram or take them to a band or a play at the
theatre or buy them chocolate and sweets or something that way. I used
to spend money on them right enough," he added, in a convincing tone, as
if he was conscious of being disbelieved.

But <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> could well believe it; he nodded gravely.

"I know that game," he said, "and it's a mug's game."

"And damn the thing I ever got out of it," said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>.

"Ditto here," said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>.

"Only off of one of them," said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>.

He moistened his upper lip by running his tongue along it. The
recollection brightened his eyes. He too gazed at the pale disc of the
moon, now nearly veiled, and seemed to meditate.

"She was ... a bit of all right," he said regretfully.

He was silent again. Then he added:

"She's on the turf now. I saw her driving down <LOCATION>Earl Street</LOCATION> one night
with two fellows with her on a car."

"I suppose that's your doing," said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>.

"There was others at her before me," said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> philosophically.

This time <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> was inclined to disbelieve. He shook his head to and
fro and smiled.

"You know you can't kid me, <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>," he said.

"Honest to God!" said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>. "Didn't she tell me herself?"

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> made a tragic gesture.

"Base betrayer!" he said.

As they passed along the railings of <ORGANIZATION>Trinity College</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> skipped
out into the road and peered up at the clock.

"Twenty after," he said.

"Time enough," said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>. "She'll be there all right. I always let her
wait a bit."

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> laughed quietly.

"Ecod! <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>, you know how to take them," he said.

"I'm up to all their little tricks," <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> confessed.

"But tell me," said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> again, "are you sure you can bring it off
all right? You know it's a ticklish job. They're damn close on that
point. Eh?... What?"

His bright, small eyes searched his companion's face for reassurance.
<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> swung his head to and fro as if to toss aside an insistent
insect, and his brows gathered.

"I'll pull it off," he said. "Leave it to me, can't you?"

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> said no more. He did not wish to ruffle his friend's temper, to
be sent to the devil and told that his advice was not wanted. A little
tact was necessary. But <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>'s brow was soon smooth again. His
thoughts were running another way.

"She's a fine decent tart," he said, with appreciation; "that's what she
is."

They walked along <LOCATION>Nassau Street</LOCATION> and then turned into <LOCATION>Kildare Street</LOCATION>. Not
far from the porch of the club a harpist stood in the roadway, playing
to a little ring of listeners. He plucked at the wires heedlessly,
glancing quickly from time to time at the face of each new-comer and
from time to time, wearily also, at the sky. His harp, too, heedless
that her coverings had fallen about her knees, seemed weary alike of the
eyes of strangers and of her master's hands. One hand played in the bass
the melody of _Silent, O <PERSON>Moyle</PERSON>_, while the other hand careered in the
treble after each group of notes. The notes of the air sounded deep and
full.

The two young men walked up the street without speaking, the mournful
music following them. When they reached <PERSON>Stephen</PERSON>'s Green they crossed the
road. Here the noise of trams, the lights and the crowd released them
from their silence.

"There she is!" said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>.

At the corner of Hume Street a young woman was standing. She wore a blue
dress and a white sailor hat. She stood on the curbstone, swinging a
sunshade in one hand. <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> grew lively.

"Let's have a look at her, <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>," he said.

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> glanced sideways at his friend and an unpleasant grin appeared on
his face.

"Are you trying to get inside me?" he asked.

"Damn it!" said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> boldly, "I don't want an introduction. All I
want is to have a look at her. I'm not going to eat her."

"O.... A look at her?" said <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>, more amiably. "Well ... I'll tell
you what. I'll go over and talk to her and you can pass by."

"Right!" said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>.

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> had already thrown one leg over the chains when <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> called
out:

"And after? Where will we meet?"

"Half ten," answered <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>, bringing over his other leg.

"Where?"

"Corner of <LOCATION>Merrion Street</LOCATION>. We'll be coming back."

"Work it all right now," said <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> in farewell.

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> did not answer. He sauntered across the road swaying his head
from side to side. His bulk, his easy pace, and the solid sound of his
boots had something of the conqueror in them. He approached the young
woman and, without saluting, began at once to converse with her. She
swung her umbrella more quickly and executed half turns on her heels.
Once or twice when he spoke to her at close quarters she laughed and
bent her head.

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> observed them for a few minutes. Then he walked rapidly along
beside the chains at some distance and crossed the road obliquely. As he
approached <LOCATION>Hume Street</LOCATION> corner he found the air heavily scented and his
eyes made a swift anxious scrutiny of the young woman's appearance. She
had her Sunday finery on. Her blue serge skirt was held at the waist by
a belt of black leather. The great silver buckle of her belt seemed to
depress the centre of her body, catching the light stuff of her white
blouse like a clip. She wore a short black jacket with mother-of-pearl
buttons and a ragged black boa. The ends of her tulle collarette had
been carefully disordered and a big bunch of red flowers was pinned in
her bosom, stems upwards. <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON>'s eyes noted approvingly her stout
short muscular body. Frank rude health glowed in her face, on her fat
red cheeks and in her unabashed blue eyes. Her features were blunt. She
had broad nostrils, a straggling mouth which lay open in a contented
leer, and two projecting front teeth. As he passed <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> took off his
cap and, after about ten seconds, <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> returned a salute to the air.
This he did by raising his hand vaguely and pensively changing the angle
of position of his hat.

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> walked as far as the <ORGANIZATION>Shelbourne Hotel</ORGANIZATION> where he halted and
waited. After waiting for a little time he saw them coming towards him
and, when they turned to the right, he followed them, stepping lightly
in his white shoes, down one side of <LOCATION>Merrion Square</LOCATION>. As he walked on
slowly, timing his pace to theirs, he watched <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>'s head which turned
at every moment towards the young woman's face like a big ball revolving
on a pivot. He kept the pair in view until he had seen them climbing the
stairs of the Donnybrook tram; then he turned about and went back the
way he had come.

Now that he was alone his face looked older. His gaiety seemed to
forsake him and, as he came by the railings of the <PERSON>Duke</PERSON>'s Lawn, he
allowed his hand to run along them. The air which the harpist had played
began to control his movements. His softly padded feet played the melody
while his fingers swept a scale of variations idly along the railings
after each group of notes.

He walked listlessly round <PERSON>Stephen</PERSON>'s Green and then down <LOCATION>Grafton Street</LOCATION>.
Though his eyes took note of many elements of the crowd through which
he passed they did so morosely. He found trivial all that was meant to
charm him and did not answer the glances which invited him to be bold.
He knew that he would have to speak a great deal, to invent and to
amuse, and his brain and throat were too dry for such a task. The
problem of how he could pass the hours till he met <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> again troubled
him a little. He could think of no way of passing them but to keep on
walking. He turned to the left when he came to the corner of <LOCATION>Rutland
Square</LOCATION> and felt more at ease in the dark quiet street, the sombre look
of which suited his mood. He paused at last before the window of a
poor-looking shop over which the words _Refreshment Bar_ were printed in
white letters. On the glass of the window were two flying inscriptions:
_Ginger Beer_ and _Ginger Ale_. A cut ham was exposed on a great blue
dish while near it on a plate lay a segment of very light plum-pudding.
He eyed this food earnestly for some time and then, after glancing
warily up and down the street, went into the shop quickly.

He was hungry for, except some biscuits which he had asked two grudging
curates to bring him, he had eaten nothing since breakfast-time. He
sat down at an uncovered wooden table opposite two work-girls and a
mechanic. A slatternly girl waited on him.

"How much is a plate of peas?" he asked.

"Three halfpence, sir," said the girl.

"Bring me a plate of peas," he said, "and a bottle of ginger beer."

He spoke roughly in order to belie his air of gentility for his entry
had been followed by a pause of talk. His face was heated. To appear
natural he pushed his cap back on his head and planted his elbows on the
table. The mechanic and the two work-girls examined him point by point
before resuming their conversation in a subdued voice. The girl brought
him a plate of grocer's hot peas, seasoned with pepper and vinegar, a
fork and his ginger beer. He ate his food greedily and found it so good
that he made a note of the shop mentally. When he had eaten all the peas
he sipped his ginger beer and sat for some time thinking of <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>'s
adventure. In his imagination he beheld the pair of lovers walking along
some dark road; he heard <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>'s voice in deep energetic gallantries
and saw again the leer of the young woman's mouth. This vision made
him feel keenly his own poverty of purse and spirit. He was tired
of knocking about, of pulling the devil by the tail, of shifts and
intrigues. He would be thirty-one in November. Would he never get a good
job? Would he never have a home of his own? He thought how pleasant it
would be to have a warm fire to sit by and a good dinner to sit down to.
He had walked the streets long enough with friends and with girls. He
knew what those friends were worth: he knew the girls too. Experience
had embittered his heart against the world. But all hope had not left
him. He felt better after having eaten than he had felt before, less
weary of his life, less vanquished in spirit. He might yet be able to
settle down in some snug corner and live happily if he could only come
across some good simple-minded girl with a little of the ready.

He paid twopence halfpenny to the slatternly girl and went out of the
shop to begin his wandering again. He went into <LOCATION>Capel Street</LOCATION> and walked
along towards the <LOCATION>City Hall</LOCATION>. Then he turned into <LOCATION>Dame Street</LOCATION>. At the
corner of <PERSON>George</PERSON>'s Street he met two friends of his and stopped to
converse with them. He was glad that he could rest from all his walking.
His friends asked him had he seen <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> and what was the latest. He
replied that he had spent the day with <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>. His friends talked
very little. They looked vacantly after some figures in the crowd and
sometimes made a critical remark. One said that he had seen Mac an hour
before in <LOCATION>Westmoreland Street</LOCATION>. At this <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> said that he had been
with Mac the night before in <PERSON>Egan</PERSON>'s. The young man who had seen Mac
in <LOCATION>Westmoreland Street</LOCATION> asked was it true that <PERSON>Mac</PERSON> had won a bit over
a billiard match. <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> did not know: he said that <PERSON>Holohan</PERSON> had stood
them drinks in <PERSON>Egan</PERSON>'s.

He left his friends at a quarter to ten and went up <PERSON>George</PERSON>'s Street.
He turned to the left at the City Markets and walked on into <LOCATION>Grafton
Street</LOCATION>. The crowd of girls and young men had thinned and on his way
up the street he heard many groups and couples bidding one another
good-night. He went as far as the clock of the College of Surgeons: it
was on the stroke of ten. He set off briskly along the northern side
of the Green hurrying for fear <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> should return too soon. When he
reached the corner of <LOCATION>Merrion Street</LOCATION> he took his stand in the shadow of
a lamp and brought out one of the cigarettes which he had reserved and
lit it. He leaned against the lamp-post and kept his gaze fixed on the
part from which he expected to see <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> and the young woman return.

His mind became active again. He wondered had <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> managed it
successfully. He wondered if he had asked her yet or if he would leave
it to the last. He suffered all the pangs and thrills of his friend's
situation as well as those of his own. But the memory of <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>'s slowly
revolving head calmed him somewhat: he was sure <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> would pull it off
all right. All at once the idea struck him that perhaps <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> had seen
her home by another way and given him the slip. His eyes searched the
street: there was no sign of them. Yet it was surely half-an-hour since
he had seen the clock of the College of Surgeons. Would <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> do
a thing like that? He lit his last cigarette and began to smoke it
nervously. He strained his eyes as each tram stopped at the far corner
of the square. They must have gone home by another way. The paper of his
cigarette broke and he flung it into the road with a curse.

Suddenly he saw them coming towards him. He started with delight and,
keeping close to his lamp-post, tried to read the result in their walk.
They were walking quickly, the young woman taking quick short steps,
while <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> kept beside her with his long stride. They did not seem to
be speaking. An intimation of the result pricked him like the point of a
sharp instrument. He knew <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> would fail; he knew it was no go.

They turned down <LOCATION>Baggot Street</LOCATION> and he followed them at once, taking the
other footpath. When they stopped he stopped too. They talked for a few
moments and then the young woman went down the steps into the area of
a house. <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> remained standing at the edge of the path, a little
distance from the front steps. Some minutes passed. Then the hall-door
was opened slowly and cautiously. A woman came running down the front
steps and coughed. <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> turned and went towards her. His broad figure
hid hers from view for a few seconds and then she reappeared running
up the steps. The door closed on her and <PERSON>Corley</PERSON> began to walk swiftly
towards <PERSON>Stephen</PERSON>'s Green.

<PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> hurried on in the same direction. Some drops of light rain fell.
He took them as a warning and, glancing back towards the house which the
young woman had entered to see that he was not observed, he ran eagerly
across the road. Anxiety and his swift run made him pant. He called out:

"Hallo, <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>!"

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> turned his head to see who had called him, and then continued
walking as before. <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> ran after him, settling the waterproof on his
shoulders with one hand.

"Hallo, <PERSON>Corley</PERSON>!" he cried again.

He came level with his friend and looked keenly in his face. He could
see nothing there.

"Well?" he said. "Did it come off?"

They had reached the corner of Ely Place. Still without answering,
<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> swerved to the left and went up the side street. His features
were composed in stern calm. <PERSON>Lenehan</PERSON> kept up with his friend, breathing
uneasily. He was baffled and a note of menace pierced through his voice.

"Can't you tell us?" he said. "Did you try her?"

<PERSON>Corley</PERSON> halted at the first lamp and stared grimly before him. Then
with a grave gesture he extended a hand towards the light and, smiling,
opened it slowly to the gaze of his disciple. A small gold coin shone in
the palm.



THE BOARDING HOUSE

<PERSON>MRS MOONEY</PERSON> was a butcher's daughter. She was a woman who was quite
able to keep things to herself: a determined woman. She had married her
father's foreman and opened a butcher's shop near <LOCATION>Spring Gardens</LOCATION>. But as
soon as his father-in-law was dead Mr <PERSON>Mooney</PERSON> began to go to the devil.
He drank, plundered the till, ran headlong into debt. It was no use
making him take the pledge: he was sure to break out again a few days
after. By fighting his wife in the presence of customers and by buying
bad meat he ruined his business. One night he went for his wife with the
cleaver and she had to sleep in a neighbour's house.