The <ORGANIZATION>Project Gutenberg EBook of This Side of Paradise</ORGANIZATION>, by <PERSON>F. Scott Fitzgerald</PERSON>



Title: This Side of Paradise

Author: <PERSON>F. Scott Fitzgerald</PERSON>

Posting Date: August 6, 2008 [EBook #805]
Release Date: February, 1997
[Last updated: June 22, 2011]

Language: English


*** START OF THIS PROJECT GUTENBERG EBOOK THIS SIDE OF PARADISE ***




Produced by <PERSON>David Reed</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Ken Reeder</PERSON>





THIS SIDE OF PARADISE

By <PERSON>F. Scott Fitzgerald</PERSON>


      ... Well this side of Paradise!...
       There's little comfort in the wise.
                              <PERSON>--Rupert Brooke</PERSON>.


       Experience is the name so many people
       give to their mistakes.
                              <PERSON>--Oscar Wilde</PERSON>.



             To SIGOURNEY FAY




CONTENTS

     BOOK ONE: The Romantic Egotist
      1.   <LOCATION>AMORY</LOCATION>, SON OF <ORGANIZATION>BEATRICE</ORGANIZATION>
      2.   SPIRES AND GARGOYLES
      3.   THE EGOTIST CONSIDERS
      4.   NARCISSUS OFF DUTY

     [INTERLUDE: MAY, 1917-FEBRUARY, 1919. ]

     BOOK TWO: The Education of a Personage
      1.   THE <ORGANIZATION>DEBUTANTE</ORGANIZATION>
      2.   EXPERIMENTS IN CONVALESCENCE
      3.   YOUNG IRONY
      4.   THE SUPERCILIOUS SACRIFICE
      5.   THE EGOTIST BECOMES A PERSONAGE





BOOK ONE--The Romantic Egotist



ineffectual, inarticulate man with a taste for <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> and a habit of
drowsing over the Encyclopedia Britannica, grew wealthy at thirty
through the death of two elder brothers, successful <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> brokers, and
in the first flush of feeling that the world was his, went to <PERSON>Bar Harbor</PERSON>
and met <PERSON>Beatrice O'Hara</PERSON>. In consequence, <PERSON>Stephen Blaine</PERSON> handed down to
posterity his height of just under six feet and his tendency to waver at
crucial moments, these two abstractions appearing in his son <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

But <PERSON>Beatrice Blaine</PERSON>! There was a woman! Early pictures taken on her
some culture even to have heard of. She learned in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> to prefer
whiskey and soda to wine, and her small talk was broadened in two senses
during a winter in <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>. All in all <PERSON>Beatrice O'Hara</PERSON> absorbed the
sort of education that will be quite impossible ever again; a tutelage
measured by the number of things and people one could be contemptuous of
and charming about; a culture rich in all arts and traditions, barren of
all ideas, in the last of those days when the great gardener clipped the
inferior roses to produce one perfect bud.

In her less important moments she returned to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, met <PERSON>Stephen
Blaine</PERSON> and married him--this almost entirely because she was a little
bit weary, a little bit sad. Her only child was carried through
a tiresome season and brought into the world on a spring day in
ninety-six.

When <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was five he was already a delightful companion for her. He
From his fourth to his tenth year he did the country with his mother
in her father's private car, from <PERSON>Coronado</PERSON>, where his mother became so
bored that she had a nervous breakdown in a fashionable hotel, down to
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, where she took a mild, almost epidemic consumption. This
trouble pleased her, and later she made use of it as an intrinsic part
of her atmosphere--especially after several astounding bracers.

So, while more or less fortunate little rich boys were defying
governesses on the beach at <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>, or being spanked or tutored or read
to from "Do and Dare," or "Frank on the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was biting
acquiescent bell-boys in the <LOCATION>Waldorf</LOCATION>, outgrowing a natural repugnance
to chamber music and symphonies, and deriving a highly specialized
education from his mother.

"Amory."


"Dear, don't _think_ of getting out of bed yet. I've always suspected
that early rising in early life makes one nervous. <PERSON>Clothilde</PERSON> is having
your breakfast brought up."

"All right."

"I am feeling very old to-day, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>," she would sigh, her face a rare
cameo of pathos, her voice exquisitely modulated, her hands as facile
as <PERSON>Bernhardt</PERSON>'s. "My nerves are on edge--on edge. We must leave this
terrifying place to-morrow and go searching for sunshine."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s penetrating green eyes would look out through tangled hair at
his mother. Even at this age he had no illusions about her.

"Amory."

"Oh, _yes_."

"I want you to take a red-hot bath as hot as you can bear it, and just
relax your nerves. You can read in the tub if you wish."

<PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> and <PERSON>Beethoven</PERSON>. One afternoon, when left alone in the hotel at
<LOCATION>Hot Springs</LOCATION>, he sampled his mother's apricot cordial, and as the taste
pleased him, he became quite tipsy. This was fun for a while, but
have been termed her "line."

"This son of mine," he heard her tell a room full of awestruck, admiring
women one day, "is entirely sophisticated and quite charming--but
delicate--we're all delicate; _here_, you know." Her hand was radiantly
was a brave raconteuse, but many were the keys turned in sideboard locks
that night against the possible defection of little <PERSON>Bobby</PERSON> or <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON>....

These domestic pilgrimages were invariably in state; two maids, the
private car, or Mr. <PERSON>Blaine</PERSON> when available, and very often a physician.
When <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had the whooping-cough four disgusted specialists glared at
each other hunched around his bed; when he took scarlet fever the number
of attendants, including physicians and nurses, totalled fourteen.

The Blaines were attached to no city. They were the <LOCATION>Blaines of Lake
Geneva</LOCATION>; they had quite enough relatives to serve in place of friends,
and an enviable standing from <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Cape Cod</LOCATION>. But <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> grew
more and more prone to like only new acquaintances, as there were
certain stories, such as the history of her constitution and its many
amendments, memories of her years abroad, that it was necessary for
her to repeat at regular intervals. Like Freudian dreams, they must be
thrown off, else they would sweep in and lay siege to her nerves. But
<PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> was critical about American women, especially the floating
population of ex-Westerners.

accent"--she became dreamy. "They pick up old, moth-eaten <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> accents
that are down on their luck and have to be used by some one. They talk
as an English butler might after several years in a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> grand-opera
once been a Catholic, but discovering that priests were infinitely more
attentive when she was in process of losing or regaining faith in <LOCATION>Mother
Church</LOCATION>, she maintained an enchantingly wavering attitude. Often she
deplored the bourgeois quality of the American Catholic clergy, and was
quite sure that had she lived in the shadow of the great <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>
cathedrals her soul would still be a thin flame on the mighty altar of

"Ah, <PERSON>Bishop Wiston</PERSON>," she would declare, "I do not want to talk of

Only to bishops and above did she divulge her clerical romance. When she
sappiness. Eventually she had decided to marry for background, and the
young pagan from <LOCATION>Asheville</LOCATION> had gone through a spiritual crisis, joined
the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>, and was now--<PERSON>Monsignor Darcy</PERSON>.

"Indeed, Mrs. <PERSON>Blaine</PERSON>, he is still delightful company--quite the
cardinal's right-hand man."

"<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> will go to him one day, I know," breathed the beautiful lady,

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> became thirteen, rather tall and slender, and more than ever on to
his Celtic mother. He had tutored occasionally--the idea being that he
was to "keep up," at each place "taking up the work where he left off,"
yet as no tutor ever found the place he left off, his mind was still in
very good shape. What a few more years of this life would have made of
him is problematical. However, four hours out from land, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> bound,
with <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>, his appendix burst, probably from too many meals in bed,
and after a series of frantic telegrams to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, to the
amazement of the passengers the great ship slowly wheeled around and
returned to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to deposit <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> at the pier. You will admit that
if it was not life it was magnificent.

uncle. There the crude, vulgar air of Western civilization first catches
him--in his underwear, so to speak.

          *****


His lip curled when he read it.

  "I am going to have a bobbing party," it said, "on Thursday,
  December the seventeenth, at five o'clock, and I would like it
  very much if you could come.

                        Yours truly,

  R.S.V.P.                                     <PERSON>Myra St. Claire</PERSON>.

He had been two months in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, and his chief struggle had been
the concealing from "the other guys at school" how particularly superior
he felt himself to be, yet this conviction was built upon shifting
sands. He had shown off one day in French class (he was in senior French
class) to the utter confusion of Mr. <PERSON>Reardon</PERSON>, whose accent <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> damned
contemptuously, and to the delight of the class. Mr. <PERSON>Reardon</PERSON>, who had
spent several weeks in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> ten years before, took his revenge on the
verbs, whenever he had his book open. But another time <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> showed off
in history class, with quite disastrous results, for the boys there
were his own age, and they shrilled innuendoes at each other all the
following week:

"Aw--I b'lieve, doncherknow, the <PERSON>Umuricun</PERSON> revolution was _lawgely_ an
affair of the middul _clawses_," or

"<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> came of very good blood--aw, quite good--I b'lieve."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> ingeniously tried to retrieve himself by blundering on purpose.
Two years before he had commenced a history of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> which,
though it only got as far as the Colonial Wars, had been pronounced by
his mother completely enchanting.

His chief disadvantage lay in athletics, but as soon as he discovered
that it was the touchstone of power and popularity at school, he began
to make furious, persistent efforts to excel in the winter sports, and
with his ankles aching and bending in spite of his efforts, he skated
valiantly around the Lorelie rink every afternoon, wondering how soon
he would be able to carry a hockey-stick without getting it inexplicably
tangled in his skates.

The invitation to Miss <PERSON>Myra St. Claire</PERSON>'s bobbing party spent the morning
in his coat pocket, where it had an intense physical affair with a dusty
piece of peanut brittle. During the afternoon he brought it to light
with a sigh, and after some consideration and a preliminary draft in the
back of Collar and <PERSON>Daniel</PERSON>'s "First-Year Latin," composed an answer:

  My dear Miss St. <PERSON>Claire</PERSON>:
  Your truly charming envitation for the evening of next Thursday
  evening was truly delightful to receive this morning.  I will be
  charm and inchanted indeed to present my compliments on next
  Thursday evening.
                          Faithfully,

                                          <PERSON>Amory Blaine</PERSON>.

          *****

On Thursday, therefore, he walked pensively along the slippery,
shovel-scraped sidewalks, and came in sight of <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>'s house, on the
half-hour after five, a lateness which he fancied his mother would
have favored. He waited on the door-step with his eyes nonchalantly
half-closed, and planned his entrance with precision. He would cross
the floor, not too hastily, to Mrs. <PERSON>St. Claire</PERSON>, and say with exactly the
correct modulation:

"My _dear_ Mrs. <PERSON>St. Claire</PERSON>, I'm _frightfully_ sorry to be late, but my
maid"--he paused there and realized he would be quoting--"but my uncle
and I had to see a fella--Yes, I've met your enchanting daughter at
dancing-school."

Then he would shake hands, using that slight, half-foreign bow, with all
the starchy little females, and nod to the fellas who would be standing
'round, paralyzed into rigid groups for mutual protection.

A butler (one of the three in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>) swung open the door. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>
stepped inside and divested himself of cap and coat. He was mildly
surprised not to hear the shrill squawk of conversation from the next
room, and he decided it must be quite formal. He approved of that--as he
approved of the butler.

"Miss <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>," he said.

To his surprise the butler grinned horribly.

"Oh, yeah," he declared, "she's here." He was unaware that his failure
to be cockney was ruining his standing. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> considered him coldly.

"But," continued the butler, his voice rising unnecessarily, "she's the
only one what _is_ here. The party's gone."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> gasped in sudden horror.

"What?"

"She's been waitin' for <PERSON>Amory Blaine</PERSON>. That's you, ain't it? Her mother
says that if you showed up by five-thirty you two was to go after 'em in
the Packard."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s despair was crystallized by the appearance of <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> herself,
bundled to the ears in a polo coat, her face plainly sulky, her voice
pleasant only with difficulty.

"'Lo, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>."

"'Lo, <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>." He had described the state of his vitality.

"Well--you _got_ here, _any_ways."

"Well--I'll tell you. I guess you don't know about the auto accident,"
he romanced.

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON>'s eyes opened wide.

"Who was it to?"

"Well," he continued desperately, "uncle 'n aunt 'n I."

"Was any one _killed?_"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> paused and then nodded.

"Your uncle?"--alarm.

"Oh, no just a horse--a sorta gray horse."

At this point the Erse butler snickered.

"Probably killed the engine," he suggested. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> would have put him on
the rack without a scruple.

"We'll go now," said <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> coolly. "You see, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, the bobs were ordered
for five and everybody was here, so we couldn't wait--"

"Well, I couldn't help it, could I?"

"So mama said for me to wait till ha'past five. We'll catch the bobs
before it gets to the <ORGANIZATION>Minnehaha Club</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s shredded poise dropped from him. He pictured the happy party
jingling along snowy streets, the appearance of the limousine, the
horrible public descent of him and <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> before sixty reproachful eyes,
his apology--a real one this time. He sighed aloud.

"What?" inquired <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>.

"Nothing. I was just yawning. Are we going to _surely_ catch up with 'em
before they get there?" He was encouraging a faint hope that they might
slip into the <ORGANIZATION>Minnehaha Club</ORGANIZATION> and meet the others there, be found in
blasé seclusion before the fire and quite regain his lost attitude.

"Oh, sure <PERSON>Mike</PERSON>, we'll catch 'em all right--let's hurry."

He became conscious of his stomach. As they stepped into the machine he
hurriedly slapped the paint of diplomacy over a rather box-like plan
he had conceived. It was based upon some "trade-lasts" gleaned at
dancing-school, to the effect that he was "awful good-looking and
_English_, sort of."

"<PERSON>Myra</PERSON>," he said, lowering his voice and choosing his words carefully,
"I beg a thousand pardons. Can you ever forgive me?" She regarded
him gravely, his intent green eyes, his mouth, that to her
thirteen-year-old, arrow-collar taste was the quintessence of romance.
Yes, <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> could forgive him very easily.

"Why--yes--sure."

He looked at her again, and then dropped his eyes. He had lashes.

"I'm awful," he said sadly. "I'm diff'runt. I don't know why I make faux
pas. 'Cause I don't care, I s'pose." Then, recklessly: "I been smoking
too much. I've got t'bacca heart."

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON> pictured an all-night tobacco debauch, with <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> pale and reeling
from the effect of nicotined lungs. She gave a little gasp.

"Oh, _<PERSON>Amory</PERSON>_, don't smoke. You'll stunt your _growth!_"

"I don't care," he persisted gloomily. "I gotta. I got the habit. I've
done a lot of things that if my fambly knew"--he hesitated, giving her
imagination time to picture dark horrors--"I went to the burlesque show
last week."

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON> was quite overcome. He turned the green eyes on her again. "You're
the only girl in town I like much," he exclaimed in a rush of sentiment.
"You're simpatico."

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON> was not sure that she was, but it sounded stylish though vaguely
improper.

Thick dusk had descended outside, and as the limousine made a sudden
turn she was jolted against him; their hands touched.

"You shouldn't smoke, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>," she whispered. "Don't you know that?"

He shook his head.

"Nobody cares."

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON> hesitated.

"_I_ care."

Something stirred within <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

"Oh, yes, you do! You got a crush on <PERSON>Froggy Parker</PERSON>. I guess everybody
knows that."

"No, I haven't," very slowly.

A silence, while <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> thrilled. There was something fascinating about
<PERSON>Myra</PERSON>, shut away here cosily from the dim, chill air. <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>, a little
bundle of clothes, with strands of yellow hair curling out from under
her skating cap.

"Because I've got a crush, too--" He paused, for he heard in the
distance the sound of young laughter, and, peering through the frosted
glass along the lamp-lit street, he made out the dark outline of the
bobbing party. He must act quickly. He reached over with a violent,
jerky effort, and clutched <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>'s hand--her thumb, to be exact.

"Tell him to go to the <LOCATION>Minnehaha</LOCATION> straight," he whispered. "I wanta talk
to you--I _got_ to talk to you."

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON> made out the party ahead, had an instant vision of her mother, and
then--alas for convention--glanced into the eyes beside. "Turn down this
side street, <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>, and drive straight to the Minnehaha Club!" she
cried through the speaking tube. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> sank back against the cushions
with a sigh of relief.

"I can kiss her," he thought. "I'll bet I can. I'll _bet_ I can!"

Overhead the sky was half crystalline, half misty, and the night around
was chill and vibrant with rich tension. From the <ORGANIZATION>Country Club</ORGANIZATION> steps the
roads stretched away, dark creases on the white blanket; huge heaps of
snow lining the sides like the tracks of giant moles. They lingered for
a moment on the steps, and watched the white holiday moon.

"Pale moons like that one"--<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> made a vague gesture--"make people
mysterieuse. You look like a young witch with her cap off and her hair
sorta mussed"--her hands clutched at her hair--"Oh, leave it, it looks
_good_."

They drifted up the stairs and <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> led the way into the little den of
his dreams, where a cosy fire was burning before a big sink-down couch.
A few years later this was to be a great stage for <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, a cradle for
many an emotional crisis. Now they talked for a moment about bobbing
parties.

"There's always a bunch of shy fellas," he commented, "sitting at the
tail of the bob, sorta lurkin' an' whisperin' an' pushin' each other
off. Then there's always some crazy cross-eyed girl"--he gave a
terrifying imitation--"she's always talkin' _hard_, sorta, to the
chaperon."

"You're such a funny boy," puzzled <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>.

"How d'y' mean?" <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> gave immediate attention, on his own ground at
last.

"Oh--always talking about crazy things. Why don't you come ski-ing with
<PERSON>Marylyn</PERSON> and I to-morrow?"

"I don't like girls in the daytime," he said shortly, and then, thinking
this a bit abrupt, he added: "But I like you." He cleared his throat. "I
like you first and second and third."

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON>'s eyes became dreamy. What a story this would make to tell
<PERSON>Marylyn</PERSON>! Here on the couch with this _wonderful_-looking boy--the little
fire--the sense that they were alone in the great building--

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON> capitulated. The atmosphere was too appropriate.

"I like you the first twenty-five," she confessed, her voice trembling,
"and <PERSON>Froggy Parker</PERSON> twenty-sixth."

<PERSON>Froggy</PERSON> had fallen twenty-five places in one hour. As yet he had not even
noticed it.

But <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, being on the spot, leaned over quickly and kissed <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>'s
cheek. He had never kissed a girl before, and he tasted his lips
curiously, as if he had munched some new fruit. Then their lips brushed
like young wild flowers in the wind.

"We're awful," rejoiced <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> gently. She slipped her hand into his,
her head drooped against his shoulder. Sudden revulsion seized <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>,
disgust, loathing for the whole incident. He desired frantically to
be away, never to see <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> again, never to kiss any one; he became
conscious of his face and hers, of their clinging hands, and he wanted
to creep out of his body and hide somewhere safe out of sight, up in the
corner of his mind.

"Kiss me again." Her voice came out of a great void.

"I don't want to," he heard himself saying. There was another pause.

"I don't want to!" he repeated passionately.

<PERSON>Myra</PERSON> sprang up, her cheeks pink with bruised vanity, the great bow on
the back of her head trembling sympathetically.

"I hate you!" she cried. "Don't you ever dare to speak to me again!"

"What?" stammered <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

"I'll tell mama you kissed me! I will too! I will too! I'll tell mama,
and she won't let me play with you!"

Amory rose and stared at her helplessly, as though she were a new animal
of whose presence on the earth he had not heretofore been aware.

The door opened suddenly, and <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>'s mother appeared on the threshold,
fumbling with her lorgnette.

"Well," she began, adjusting it benignantly, "the man at the desk told
me you two children were up here--How do you do, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> watched <PERSON>Myra</PERSON> and waited for the crash--but none came. The pout
faded, the high pink subsided, and <PERSON>Myra</PERSON>'s voice was placid as a summer
lake when she answered her mother.

"Oh, we started so late, mama, that I thought we might as well--"

He heard from below the shrieks of laughter, and smelled the vapid
odor of hot chocolate and tea-cakes as he silently followed mother and
daughter down-stairs. The sound of the graphophone mingled with the
voices of many girls humming the air, and a faint glow was born and
spread over him:

   "Casey-Jones--mounted to the cab-un
    Casey-Jones--'th his orders in his hand.
    Casey-Jones--mounted to the cab-un
    Took his farewell journey to the prom-ised land."

          *****

SNAPSHOTS OF THE YOUNG EGOTIST

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> spent nearly two years in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>. The first winter he wore
moccasins that were born yellow, but after many applications of oil and
dirt assumed their mature color, a dirty, greenish brown; he wore a gray
plaid mackinaw coat, and a red toboggan cap. His dog, Count <PERSON>Del Monte</PERSON>,
ate the red cap, so his uncle gave him a gray one that pulled down over
his face. The trouble with this one was that you breathed into it and
your breath froze; one day the darn thing froze his cheek. He rubbed
snow on his cheek, but it turned bluish-black just the same.

          *****

The Count <PERSON>Del Monte</PERSON> ate a box of bluing once, but it didn't hurt him.
Later, however, he lost his mind and ran madly up the street, bumping
into fences, rolling in gutters, and pursuing his eccentric course out
of <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s life. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> cried on his bed.

"Poor little Count," he cried. "Oh, _poor_ little _Count!_"

After several months he suspected Count of a fine piece of emotional
acting.

          *****

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> and <PERSON>Frog Parker</PERSON> considered that the greatest line in literature
occurred in Act III of "<PERSON>Arsene Lupin</PERSON>."

They sat in the first row at the Wednesday and Saturday matinees. The
line was:

"If one can't be a great artist or a great soldier, the next best thing
is to be a great criminal."

          *****

Amory fell in love again, and wrote a poem. This was it:

   "<PERSON>Marylyn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sallee</PERSON>,
    Those are the girls for me.
    <PERSON>Marylyn</PERSON> stands above
    <PERSON>Sallee</PERSON> in that sweet, deep love."

He was interested in whether <PERSON>McGovern</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> would make the
first or second All-American, how to do the card-pass, how to do
the coin-pass, chameleon ties, how babies were born, and whether
Three-fingered <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> was really a better pitcher than <PERSON>Christie
Mathewson</PERSON>.

Among other things he read: "For the Honor of the School," "Little
Women" (twice), "The Common Law," "Sapho," "Dangerous <PERSON>Dan McGrew</PERSON>," "The
Broad Highway" (three times), "The Fall of the <ORGANIZATION>House of Usher</ORGANIZATION>," "Three
Weeks," "<PERSON>Mary Ware</PERSON>, the Little Colonel's Chum," "Gunga Din," The Police
Gazette, and Jim-Jam Jems.

He had all the Henty biasses in history, and was particularly fond of
the cheerful murder stories of <PERSON>Mary Roberts Rinehart</PERSON>.

          *****

School ruined his French and gave him a distaste for standard authors.
His masters considered him idle, unreliable and superficially clever.

          *****

He collected locks of hair from many girls. He wore the rings of
several. Finally he could borrow no more rings, owing to his nervous
habit of chewing them out of shape. This, it seemed, usually aroused the
jealous suspicions of the next borrower.

          *****

All through the summer months <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> and <PERSON>Frog Parker</PERSON> went each week to
the <ORGANIZATION>Stock Company</ORGANIZATION>. Afterward they would stroll home in the balmy air of
August night, dreaming along <LOCATION>Hennepin</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Nicollet Avenues</ORGANIZATION>, through the
gay crowd. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> wondered how people could fail to notice that he was a
boy marked for glory, and when faces of the throng turned toward him
and ambiguous eyes stared into his, he assumed the most romantic of
expressions and walked on the air cushions that lie on the asphalts of
fourteen.

Always, after he was in bed, there were voices--indefinite, fading,
enchanting--just outside his window, and before he fell asleep he would
dream one of his favorite waking dreams, the one about becoming a great
half-back, or the one about the Japanese invasion, when he was rewarded
by being made the youngest general in the world. It was always
the becoming he dreamed of, never the being. This, too, was quite
characteristic of <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

          *****

CODE OF THE YOUNG EGOTIST

Before he was summoned back to <LOCATION>Lake Geneva</LOCATION>, he had appeared, shy but
inwardly glowing, in his first long trousers, set off by a purple
accordion tie and a "Belmont" collar with the edges unassailably
meeting, purple socks, and handkerchief with a purple border peeping
from his breast pocket. But more than that, he had formulated his first
philosophy, a code to live by, which, as near as it can be named, was a
sort of aristocratic egotism.

He had realized that his best interests were bound up with those of a
certain variant, changing person, whose label, in order that his past
might always be identified with him, was <PERSON>Amory Blaine</PERSON>. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> marked
himself a fortunate youth, capable of infinite expansion for good or
evil. He did not consider himself a "strong char'c'ter," but relied on
his facility (learn things sorta quick) and his superior mentality (read
a lotta deep books). He was proud of the fact that he could never
become a mechanical or scientific genius. From no other heights was he
debarred.

Physically.<PERSON>--Amory</PERSON> thought that he was exceedingly handsome. He was. He
fancied himself an athlete of possibilities and a supple dancer.

Socially.--Here his condition was, perhaps, most dangerous. He granted
himself personality, charm, magnetism, poise, the power of dominating
all contemporary males, the gift of fascinating all women.

Mentally.--Complete, unquestioned superiority.

Now a confession will have to be made. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had rather a Puritan
conscience. Not that he yielded to it--later in life he almost
completely slew it--but at fifteen it made him consider himself a
great deal worse than other boys... unscrupulousness... the desire
to influence people in almost every way, even for evil... a certain
coldness and lack of affection, amounting sometimes to cruelty... a
shifting sense of honor... an unholy selfishness... a puzzled, furtive
interest in everything concerning sex.

There was, also, a curious strain of weakness running crosswise through
his make-up... a harsh phrase from the lips of an older boy (older boys
usually detested him) was liable to sweep him off his poise into surly
sensitiveness, or timid stupidity... he was a slave to his own moods
and he felt that though he was capable of recklessness and audacity, he
possessed neither courage, perseverance, nor self-respect.

Vanity, tempered with self-suspicion if not self-knowledge, a sense of
people as automatons to his will, a desire to "pass" as many boys as
possible and get to a vague top of the world... with this background did
<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> drift into adolescence.

          *****

PREPARATORY TO THE GREAT ADVENTURE

The train slowed up with midsummer languor at <LOCATION>Lake Geneva</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>
caught sight of his mother waiting in her electric on the gravelled
station drive. It was an ancient electric, one of the early types, and
painted gray. The sight of her sitting there, slenderly erect, and
of her face, where beauty and dignity combined, melting to a dreamy
recollected smile, filled him with a sudden great pride of her. As they
kissed coolly and he stepped into the electric, he felt a quick fear
lest he had lost the requisite charm to measure up to her.

"Dear boy--you're _so_ tall... look behind and see if there's anything
coming..."

She looked left and right, she slipped cautiously into a speed of two
miles an hour, beseeching <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> to act as sentinel; and at one busy
crossing she made him get out and run ahead to signal her forward like a
traffic policeman. <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> was what might be termed a careful driver.

"You _are_ tall--but you're still very handsome--you've skipped the
awkward age, or is that sixteen; perhaps it's fourteen or fifteen; I can
never remember; but you've skipped it."

"Don't embarrass me," murmured <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

"But, my dear boy, what odd clothes! They look as if they were a
_set_--don't they? Is your underwear purple, too?"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> grunted impolitely.

"You must go to <PERSON>Brooks</PERSON>' and get some really nice suits. Oh, we'll have a
talk to-night or perhaps to-morrow night. I want to tell you about
your heart--you've probably been neglecting your heart--and you don't
_know_."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> thought how superficial was the recent overlay of his own
generation. Aside from a minute shyness, he felt that the old cynical
kinship with his mother had not been one bit broken. Yet for the first
few days he wandered about the gardens and along the shore in a state
of superloneliness, finding a lethargic content in smoking "Bull" at the
garage with one of the chauffeurs.

The sixty acres of the estate were dotted with old and new summer houses
and many fountains and white benches that came suddenly into sight from
foliage-hung hiding-places; there was a great and constantly increasing
family of white cats that prowled the many flower-beds and were
silhouetted suddenly at night against the darkening trees. It was on
one of the shadowy paths that <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> at last captured <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, after Mr.
<PERSON>Blaine</PERSON> had, as usual, retired for the evening to his private library.
After reproving him for avoiding her, she took him for a long
tete-a-tete in the moonlight. He could not reconcile himself to her
beauty, that was mother to his own, the exquisite neck and shoulders,
the grace of a fortunate woman of thirty.

"Amory, dear," she crooned softly, "I had such a strange, weird time
after I left you."

"Did you, <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>?"

"When I had my last breakdown"--she spoke of it as a sturdy, gallant
feat.

"The doctors told me"--her voice sang on a confidential note--"that if
any man alive had done the consistent drinking that I have, he would
have been physically _shattered_, my dear, and in his _grave_--long in
his grave."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> winced, and wondered how this would have sounded to <PERSON>Froggy Parker</PERSON>.

"Yes," continued <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> tragically, "I had dreams--wonderful visions."
She pressed the palms of her hands into her eyes. "I saw bronze rivers
lapping marble shores, and great birds that soared through the air,
parti-colored birds with iridescent plumage. I heard strange music and
the flare of barbaric trumpets--what?"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had snickered.

"What, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>?"

"I said go on, <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>."

"That was all--it merely recurred and recurred--gardens that flaunted
coloring against which this would be quite dull, moons that whirled and
swayed, paler than winter moons, more golden than harvest moons--"

"Are you quite well now, <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>?"

"Quite well--as well as I will ever be. I am not understood, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>. I
know that can't express it to you, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, but--I am not understood."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was quite moved. He put his arm around his mother, rubbing his
head gently against her shoulder.

"Poor <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>--poor <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>."

"Tell me about _you_, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>. Did you have two _horrible_ years?"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> considered lying, and then decided against it.

"No, <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>. I enjoyed them. I adapted myself to the bourgeoisie.
I became conventional." He surprised himself by saying that, and he
pictured how <PERSON>Froggy</PERSON> would have gaped.

"Beatrice," he said suddenly, "I want to go away to school. Everybody in
<LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> is going to go away to school."

<PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> showed some alarm.

"But you're only fifteen."

"Yes, but everybody goes away to school at fifteen, and I _want_ to,
<PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>."

On <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>'s suggestion the subject was dropped for the rest of the
walk, but a week later she delighted him by saying:

"Amory, I have decided to let you have your way. If you still want to,
you can go to school."

"Yes?"

"To St. Regis's in <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> felt a quick excitement.

"It's being arranged," continued <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>. "It's better that you should
go away. I'd have preferred you to have gone to <LOCATION>Eton</LOCATION>, and then to <ORGANIZATION>Christ
Church</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oxford</LOCATION>, but it seems impracticable now--and for the present
we'll let the university question take care of itself."

"What are you going to do, <PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON>?"

"Heaven knows. It seems my fate to fret away my years in this country.
Not for a second do I regret being American--indeed, I think that a
regret typical of very vulgar people, and I feel sure we are the great
coming nation--yet"--and she sighed--"I feel my life should have drowsed
away close to an older, mellower civilization, a land of greens and
autumnal browns--"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> did not answer, so his mother continued:

"My regret is that you haven't been abroad, but still, as you are a man,
it's better that you should grow up here under the snarling eagle--is
that the right term?"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> agreed that it was. She would not have appreciated the Japanese
invasion.

"When do I go to school?"

"Next month. You'll have to start East a little early to take your
examinations. After that you'll have a free week, so I want you to go up
the <LOCATION>Hudson</LOCATION> and pay a visit."

"To who?"

"To Monsignor <PERSON>Darcy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>. He wants to see you. He went to <PERSON>Harrow</PERSON> and
then to <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>--became a Catholic. I want him to talk to you--I feel he
can be such a help--" She stroked his auburn hair gently. "Dear Amory,
dear Amory--"

"Dear Beatrice--"

          *****

So early in September Amory, provided with "six suits summer underwear,
six suits winter underwear, one sweater or T shirt, one jersey, one
overcoat, winter, etc.," set out for <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, the land of schools.

There were <LOCATION>Andover</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Exeter</LOCATION> with their memories of <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>
dead--large, college-like democracies; <LOCATION>St. Mark's</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Groton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St.
Regis</LOCATION>'--recruited from <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> and the Knickerbocker families of <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>St. Paul's</ORGANIZATION>, with its great rinks; <LOCATION>Pomfret</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St. George's</LOCATION>,
prosperous and well-dressed; <PERSON>Taft</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hotchkiss</PERSON>, which prepared
the wealth of the <LOCATION>Middle West</LOCATION> for social success at <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>; <LOCATION>Pawling</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Choate</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kent</PERSON>, and a hundred others; all milling out their
well-set-up, conventional, impressive type, year after year; their
mental stimulus the college entrance exams; their vague purpose set
forth in a hundred circulars as "To impart a Thorough Mental, Moral, and
Physical Training as a Christian Gentleman, to fit the boy for meeting
the problems of his day and generation, and to give a solid foundation
in the Arts and Sciences."

At <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>' <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> stayed three days and took his exams with a scoffing
confidence, then doubling back to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to pay his tutelary visit.
The metropolis, barely glimpsed, made little impression on him, except
for the sense of cleanliness he drew from the tall white buildings seen
from a <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> steamboat in the early morning. Indeed, his mind was
so crowded with dreams of athletic prowess at school that he considered
this visit only as a rather tiresome prelude to the great adventure.
This, however, it did not prove to be.

Monsignor <PERSON>Darcy</PERSON>'s house was an ancient, rambling structure set on a hill
overlooking the river, and there lived its owner, between his trips to
all parts of the Roman-Catholic world, rather like an exiled Stuart king
waiting to be called to the rule of his land. Monsignor was forty-four
then, and bustling--a trifle too stout for symmetry, with hair the color
of spun gold, and a brilliant, enveloping personality. When he came into
a room clad in his full purple regalia from thatch to toe, he resembled
a <ORGANIZATION>Turner</ORGANIZATION> sunset, and attracted both admiration and attention. He had
written two novels: one of them violently anti-Catholic, just before his
conversion, and five years later another, in which he had attempted
to turn all his clever jibes against Catholics into even cleverer
innuendoes against Episcopalians. He was intensely ritualistic,
startlingly dramatic, loved the idea of God enough to be a celibate, and
rather liked his neighbor.

Children adored him because he was like a child; youth revelled in his
company because he was still a youth, and couldn't be shocked. In the
proper land and century he might have been a Richelieu--at present he
was a very moral, very religious (if not particularly pious) clergyman,
making a great mystery about pulling rusty wires, and appreciating life
to the fullest, if not entirely enjoying it.

He and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> took to each other at first sight--the jovial, impressive
prelate who could dazzle an embassy ball, and the green-eyed, intent
youth, in his first long trousers, accepted in their own minds a
relation of father and son within a half-hour's conversation.

"My dear boy, I've been waiting to see you for years. Take a big chair
and we'll have a chat."

"I've just come from school--<LOCATION>St. Regis</LOCATION>'s, you know."

"So your mother says--a remarkable woman; have a cigarette--I'm sure
you smoke. Well, if you're like me, you loathe all science and
mathematics--"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> nodded vehemently.

"Hate 'em all. Like English and history."

"Of course. You'll hate school for a while, too, but I'm glad you're
going to <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>'s."

"Why?"

"Because it's a gentleman's school, and democracy won't hit you so
early. You'll find plenty of that in college."

"I want to go to <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>. "I don't know why, but I think
of all <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> men as sissies, like I used to be, and all <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> men as
wearing big blue sweaters and smoking pipes."

Monsignor chuckled.

"I'm one, you know."

"Oh, you're different--I think of <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION> as being lazy and
good-looking and aristocratic--you know, like a spring day. <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>
seems sort of indoors--"

"And <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> is November, crisp and energetic," finished Monsignor.

"That's it."

They slipped briskly into an intimacy from which they never recovered.

"I was for <PERSON>Bonnie Prince Charlie</PERSON>," announced <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

"Of course you were--and for <PERSON>Hannibal</PERSON>--"

"Yes, and for the Southern Confederacy." He was rather sceptical about
being an Irish patriot--he suspected that being Irish was being somewhat
common--but <PERSON>Monsignor</PERSON> assured him that <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> was a romantic lost cause
and Irish people quite charming, and that it should, by all means, be
one of his principal biasses.

After a crowded hour which included several more cigarettes, and during
which Monsignor learned, to his surprise but not to his horror, that
<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had not been brought up a Catholic, he announced that he had
another guest. This turned out to be the Honorable <PERSON>Thornton Hancock</PERSON>, of
<LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, ex-minister to <LOCATION>The Hague</LOCATION>, author of an erudite history of the
Middle Ages and the last of a distinguished, patriotic, and brilliant
family.

"He comes here for a rest," said Monsignor confidentially, treating
<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> as a contemporary. "I act as an escape from the weariness of
agnosticism, and I think I'm the only man who knows how his staid old
mind is really at sea and longs for a sturdy spar like the Church to
cling to."

Their first luncheon was one of the memorable events of <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s early
life. He was quite radiant and gave off a peculiar brightness and
charm. Monsignor called out the best that he had thought by question and
suggestion, and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> talked with an ingenious brilliance of a thousand
impulses and desires and repulsions and faiths and fears. He and
Monsignor held the floor, and the older man, with his less receptive,
less accepting, yet certainly not colder mentality, seemed content to
listen and bask in the mellow sunshine that played between these two.
Monsignor gave the effect of sunlight to many people; <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> gave it in
his youth and, to some extent, when he was very much older, but never
again was it quite so mutually spontaneous.

"He's a radiant boy," thought <PERSON>Thornton Hancock</PERSON>, who had seen the
splendor of two continents and talked with <PERSON>Parnell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gladstone</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>--and afterward he added to Monsignor: "But his education ought
not to be intrusted to a school or college."

But for the next four years the best of <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s intellect was
concentrated on matters of popularity, the intricacies of a university
social system and <ORGANIZATION>American Society</ORGANIZATION> as represented by <PERSON>Biltmore Teas</PERSON> and
Hot Springs golf-links.

... In all, a wonderful week, that saw <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s mind turned inside out, a
hundred of his theories confirmed, and his joy of life crystallized to
a thousand ambitions. Not that the conversation was scholastic--heaven
forbid! <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had only the vaguest idea as to what <PERSON>Bernard Shaw</PERSON> was--but
<PERSON>Monsignor</PERSON> made quite as much out of "The Beloved Vagabond" and "Sir
<PERSON>Nigel</PERSON>," taking good care that <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> never once felt out of his depth.

But the trumpets were sounding for <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s preliminary skirmish with his
own generation.

"You're not sorry to go, of course. With people like us our home is
where we are not," said Monsignor.

"I _am_ sorry--"

"No, you're not. No one person in the world is necessary to you or to
me."

"Well--"

"Good-by."

          *****

THE EGOTIST DOWN

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s two years at <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>', though in turn painful and triumphant,
had as little real significance in his own life as the American "prep"
school, crushed as it is under the heel of the universities, has
to American life in general. We have no <ORGANIZATION>Eton</ORGANIZATION> to create the
self-consciousness of a governing class; we have, instead, clean,
flaccid and innocuous preparatory schools.

He went all wrong at the start, was generally considered both conceited
and arrogant, and universally detested. He played football intensely,
alternating a reckless brilliancy with a tendency to keep himself as
safe from hazard as decency would permit. In a wild panic he backed out
of a fight with a boy his own size, to a chorus of scorn, and a week
later, in desperation, picked a battle with another boy very much
bigger, from which he emerged badly beaten, but rather proud of himself.

He was resentful against all those in authority over him, and this,
combined with a lazy indifference toward his work, exasperated every
master in school. He grew discouraged and imagined himself a pariah;
took to sulking in corners and reading after lights. With a dread of
being alone he attached a few friends, but since they were not among
the elite of the school, he used them simply as mirrors of himself,
audiences before which he might do that posing absolutely essential to
him. He was unbearably lonely, desperately unhappy.

There were some few grains of comfort. Whenever <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was submerged,
his vanity was the last part to go below the surface, so he could still
enjoy a comfortable glow when "Wookey-wookey," the deaf old housekeeper,
told him that he was the best-looking boy she had ever seen. It had
pleased him to be the lightest and youngest man on the first football
squad; it pleased him when Doctor <PERSON>Dougall</PERSON> told him at the end of a
heated conference that he could, if he wished, get the best marks in
school. But Doctor <PERSON>Dougall</PERSON> was wrong. It was temperamentally impossible
for <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> to get the best marks in school.

Miserable, confined to bounds, unpopular with both faculty and
students--that was <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s first term. But at Christmas he had returned
to <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, tight-lipped and strangely jubilant.

"Oh, I was sort of fresh at first," he told <PERSON>Frog Parker</PERSON> patronizingly,
"but I got along fine--lightest man on the squad. You ought to go away
to school, Froggy. It's great stuff."

          *****

INCIDENT OF THE WELL-MEANING PROFESSOR

On the last night of his first term, Mr. <PERSON>Margotson</PERSON>, the senior master,
sent word to study hall that <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was to come to his room at nine.
<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> suspected that advice was forthcoming, but he determined to be
courteous, because this Mr. <PERSON>Margotson</PERSON> had been kindly disposed toward
him.

His summoner received him gravely, and motioned him to a chair. He
hemmed several times and looked consciously kind, as a man will when he
knows he's on delicate ground.

"Amory," he began. "I've sent for you on a personal matter."

"Yes, sir."

"I've noticed you this year and I--I like you. I think you have in you
the makings of a--a very good man."

"Yes, sir," <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> managed to articulate. He hated having people talk as
if he were an admitted failure.

"But I've noticed," continued the older man blindly, "that you're not
very popular with the boys."

"No, sir." <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> licked his lips.

"Ah--I thought you might not understand exactly what it
was they--ah--objected to. I'm going to tell you, because I
believe--ah--that when a boy knows his difficulties he's better able to
cope with them--to conform to what others expect of him." He a-hemmed
again with delicate reticence, and continued: "They seem to think that
you're--ah--rather too fresh--"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> could stand no more. He rose from his chair, scarcely controlling
his voice when he spoke.

"I know--oh, _don't_ you s'pose I know." His voice rose. "I know what
they think; do you s'pose you have to _tell_ me!" He paused. "I'm--I've
got to go back now--hope I'm not rude--"

He left the room hurriedly. In the cool air outside, as he walked to his
house, he exulted in his refusal to be helped.

"That _damn_ old fool!" he cried wildly. "As if I didn't _know!_"

He decided, however, that this was a good excuse not to go back to study
hall that night, so, comfortably couched up in his room, he munched
<PERSON>Nabiscos</PERSON> and finished "<ORGANIZATION>The White Company</ORGANIZATION>."

          *****

INCIDENT OF THE WONDERFUL GIRL

There was a bright star in February. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> burst upon him on
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s Birthday with the brilliance of a long-anticipated event.
His glimpse of it as a vivid whiteness against a deep-blue sky had left
a picture of splendor that rivalled the dream cities in the Arabian
Nights; but this time he saw it by electric light, and romance gleamed
from the chariot-race sign on <LOCATION>Broadway</LOCATION> and from the women's eyes at the
<LOCATION>Astor</LOCATION>, where he and young <PERSON>Paskert</PERSON> from <LOCATION>St. Regis</LOCATION>' had dinner. When they
walked down the aisle of the theatre, greeted by the nervous twanging
and discord of untuned violins and the sensuous, heavy fragrance of
paint and powder, he moved in a sphere of epicurean delight. Everything
enchanted him. The play was "The Little Millionaire," with <PERSON>George M.
Cohan</PERSON>, and there was one stunning young brunette who made him sit with
brimming eyes in the ecstasy of watching her dance.

   "Oh--you--wonderful girl,
    What a wonderful girl you are--"

sang the tenor, and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> agreed silently, but passionately.

   "All--your--wonderful words
    Thrill me through--"

The violins swelled and quavered on the last notes, the girl sank to a
crumpled butterfly on the stage, a great burst of clapping filled the
house. Oh, to fall in love like that, to the languorous magic melody of
such a tune!

The last scene was laid on a roof-garden, and the 'cellos sighed to the
musical moon, while light adventure and facile froth-like comedy flitted
back and forth in the calcium. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was on fire to be an habitui of
roof-gardens, to meet a girl who should look like that--better, that
very girl; whose hair would be drenched with golden moonlight, while at
his elbow sparkling wine was poured by an unintelligible waiter. When
the curtain fell for the last time he gave such a long sigh that the
people in front of him twisted around and stared and said loud enough
for him to hear:

"What a _remarkable_-looking boy!"

This took his mind off the play, and he wondered if he really did seem
handsome to the population of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.

Paskert and he walked in silence toward their hotel. The former was
the first to speak. His uncertain fifteen-year-old voice broke in in a
melancholy strain on <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s musings:

"I'd marry that girl to-night."

There was no need to ask what girl he referred to.

"I'd be proud to take her home and introduce her to my people,"
continued Paskert.

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was distinctly impressed. He wished he had said it instead of
<LOCATION>Paskert</LOCATION>. It sounded so mature.

"I wonder about actresses; are they all pretty bad?"

"No, _sir_, not by a darn sight," said the worldly youth with emphasis,
"and I know that girl's as good as gold. I can tell."

They wandered on, mixing in the <LOCATION>Broadway</LOCATION> crowd, dreaming on the music
that eddied out of the cafes. New faces flashed on and off like
myriad lights, pale or rouged faces, tired, yet sustained by a weary
excitement. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> watched them in fascination. He was planning his life.
He was going to live in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, and be known at every restaurant and
cafe, wearing a dress-suit from early evening to early morning, sleeping
away the dull hours of the forenoon.

"Yes, _sir_, I'd marry that girl to-night!"

          *****

HEROIC IN GENERAL TONE

October of his second and last year at <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>' was a high point in
<PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s memory. The game with <LOCATION>Groton</LOCATION> was played from three of a snappy,
exhilarating afternoon far into the crisp autumnal twilight, and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>
at quarter-back, exhorting in wild despair, making impossible tackles,
calling signals in a voice that had diminished to a hoarse, furious
whisper, yet found time to revel in the blood-stained bandage around his
head, and the straining, glorious heroism of plunging, crashing bodies
and aching limbs. For those minutes courage flowed like wine out of the
November dusk, and he was the eternal hero, one with the sea-rover on
the prow of a Norse galley, one with <PERSON>Roland</PERSON> and Horatius, Sir <PERSON>Nigel</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Ted Coy</PERSON>, scraped and stripped into trim and then flung by his own will
into the breach, beating back the tide, hearing from afar the thunder of
cheers... finally bruised and weary, but still elusive, circling an end,
twisting, changing pace, straight-arming... falling behind the <LOCATION>Groton</LOCATION>
goal with two men on his legs, in the only touchdown of the game.

          *****

THE PHILOSOPHY OF THE SLICKER

From the scoffing superiority of sixth-form year and success <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>
looked back with cynical wonder on his status of the year before. He was
changed as completely as <PERSON>Amory Blaine</PERSON> could ever be changed. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> plus
<PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> plus two years in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>--these had been his ingredients
when he entered St. Regis'. But the <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> years were not a thick
enough overlay to conceal the "Amory plus Beatrice" from the ferreting
eyes of a boarding-school, so <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>' had very painfully drilled
<PERSON>Beatrice</PERSON> out of him, and begun to lay down new and more conventional
planking on the fundamental <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>. But both St. Regis' and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> were
unconscious of the fact that this fundamental <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had not in himself
changed. Those qualities for which he had suffered, his moodiness, his
tendency to pose, his laziness, and his love of playing the fool, were
now taken as a matter of course, recognized eccentricities in a star
quarter-back, a clever actor, and the editor of the St. Regis Tattler:
it puzzled him to see impressionable small boys imitating the very
vanities that had not long ago been contemptible weaknesses.

After the football season he slumped into dreamy content. The night
of the pre-holiday dance he slipped away and went early to bed for the
pleasure of hearing the violin music cross the grass and come surging in
at his window. Many nights he lay there dreaming awake of secret cafes
in <PERSON>Mont Martre</PERSON>, where ivory women delved in romantic mysteries with
diplomats and soldiers of fortune, while orchestras played Hungarian
waltzes and the air was thick and exotic with intrigue and moonlight
and adventure. In the spring he read "L'Allegro," by request, and was
inspired to lyrical outpourings on the subject of <PERSON>Arcady</PERSON> and the pipes
of Pan. He moved his bed so that the sun would wake him at dawn that he
might dress and go out to the archaic swing that hung from an apple-tree
near the sixth-form house. Seating himself in this he would pump higher
and higher until he got the effect of swinging into the wide air, into
a fairyland of piping satyrs and nymphs with the faces of fair-haired
girls he passed in the streets of <LOCATION>Eastchester</LOCATION>. As the swing reached its
highest point, <PERSON>Arcady</PERSON> really lay just over the brow of a certain hill,
where the brown road dwindled out of sight in a golden dot.

He read voluminously all spring, the beginning of his eighteenth year:
"The Gentleman from <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>," "The New Arabian Nights," "The Morals
of <PERSON>Marcus Ordeyne</PERSON>," "The Man Who Was Thursday," which he liked without
understanding; "<PERSON>Stover</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>," that became somewhat of a text-book;
"Dombey and Son," because he thought he really should read better
stuff; <PERSON>Robert Chambers</PERSON>, <PERSON>David Graham Phillips</PERSON>, and <PERSON>E. Phillips Oppenheim</PERSON>
complete, and a scattering of <PERSON>Tennyson</PERSON> and Kipling. Of all his class
work only "L'Allegro" and some quality of rigid clarity in solid
geometry stirred his languid interest.

As June drew near, he felt the need of conversation to formulate his
own ideas, and, to his surprise, found a co-philosopher in <PERSON>Rahill</PERSON>, the
president of the sixth form. In many a talk, on the highroad or lying
belly-down along the edge of the baseball diamond, or late at night with
their cigarettes glowing in the dark, they threshed out the questions of
school, and there was developed the term "slicker."

"Got tobacco?" whispered <PERSON>Rahill</PERSON> one night, putting his head inside the
door five minutes after lights.

"Sure."

"I'm coming in."

"Take a couple of pillows and lie in the window-seat, why don't you."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> sat up in bed and lit a cigarette while <PERSON>Rahill</PERSON> settled for a
conversation. <PERSON>Rahill</PERSON>'s favorite subject was the respective futures of
the sixth form, and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> never tired of outlining them for his benefit.

"Ted Converse? 'At's easy. He'll fail his exams, tutor all summer at
<ORGANIZATION>Harstrum</ORGANIZATION>'s, get into Sheff with about four conditions, and flunk out in
the middle of the freshman year. Then he'll go back West and raise hell
for a year or so; finally his father will make him go into the paint
business. He'll marry and have four sons, all bone heads. He'll always
think St. Regis's spoiled him, so he'll send his sons to day school in
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>. He'll die of locomotor ataxia when he's forty-one, and
his wife will give a baptizing stand or whatever you call it to the
<ORGANIZATION>Presbyterian Church</ORGANIZATION>, with his name on it--"

"Hold up, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>. That's too darned gloomy. How about yourself?"

"I'm in a superior class. You are, too. We're philosophers."

"I'm not."

"Sure you are. You've got a darn good head on you." But <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> knew that
nothing in the abstract, no theory or generality, ever moved <PERSON>Rahill</PERSON>
until he stubbed his toe upon the concrete minutiae of it.

"Haven't," insisted <PERSON>Rahill</PERSON>. "I let people impose on me here and don't
get anything out of it. I'm the prey of my friends, damn it--do their
lessons, get 'em out of trouble, pay 'em stupid summer visits, and
always entertain their kid sisters; keep my temper when they get selfish
and then they think they pay me back by voting for me and telling me I'm
the 'big man' of <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>'s. I want to get where everybody does their
own work and I can tell people where to go. I'm tired of being nice to
every poor fish in school."

"You're not a slicker," said <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> suddenly.

"A what?"

"A slicker."

"What the devil's that?"

"Well, it's something that--that--there's a lot of them. You're not one,
and neither am I, though I am more than you are."

"Who is one? What makes you one?"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> considered.

"Why--why, I suppose that the _sign_ of it is when a fellow slicks his
hair back with water."

"Like <PERSON>Carstairs</PERSON>?"

"Yes--sure. He's a slicker."

They spent two evenings getting an exact definition. The slicker was
good-looking or clean-looking; he had brains, social brains, that is,
and he used all means on the broad path of honesty to get ahead,
be popular, admired, and never in trouble. He dressed well, was
particularly neat in appearance, and derived his name from the fact that
his hair was inevitably worn short, soaked in water or tonic, parted
in the middle, and slicked back as the current of fashion dictated. The
slickers of that year had adopted tortoise-shell spectacles as badges
of their slickerhood, and this made them so easy to recognize that <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Rahill</PERSON> never missed one. The slicker seemed distributed through
school, always a little wiser and shrewder than his contemporaries,
managing some team or other, and keeping his cleverness carefully
concealed.

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> found the slicker a most valuable classification until his junior
year in college, when the outline became so blurred and indeterminate
that it had to be subdivided many times, and became only a quality.
<PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s secret ideal had all the slicker qualifications, but, in
addition, courage and tremendous brains and talents--also <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> conceded
him a bizarre streak that was quite irreconcilable to the slicker
proper.

This was a first real break from the hypocrisy of school tradition. The
slicker was a definite element of success, differing intrinsically from
the prep school "big man."


  "THE SLICKER"

 1. Clever sense of social values.

 2. Dresses well.  Pretends that dress is superficial--but knows that it isn't.

 3. Goes into such activities as he can shine in.

 4. Gets to college and is, in a worldly way, successful.

 5. Hair slicked.


  "THE BIG MAN"

 1. Inclined to stupidity and unconscious of social values.

 2. Thinks dress is superficial, and is inclined to be
    careless about it.

 3. Goes out for everything from a sense of duty.

 4. Gets to college and has a problematical future.  Feels lost
    without his circle, and always says that school days were
    happiest, after all.  Goes back to school and makes speeches
    about what St. Regis's boys are doing.

 5. Hair not slicked.

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had decided definitely on <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION>, even though he would be the
only boy entering that year from <LOCATION>St. Regis</LOCATION>'. <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> had a romance and
glamour from the tales of <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, and St. Regis' men who had been
"tapped for Skull and Bones," but <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> drew him most, with
its atmosphere of bright colors and its alluring reputation as the
pleasantest country club in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. Dwarfed by the menacing college
exams, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s school days drifted into the past. Years afterward, when
he went back to <PERSON>St. Regis</PERSON>', he seemed to have forgotten the successes
of sixth-form year, and to be able to picture himself only as the
unadjustable boy who had hurried down corridors, jeered at by his rabid
contemporaries mad with common sense.



CHAPTER 2. Spires and Gargoyles


At first Amory noticed only the wealth of sunshine creeping across the
long, green swards, dancing on the leaded window-panes, and swimming
around the tops of spires and towers and battlemented walls.
Gradually he realized that he was really walking up <ORGANIZATION>University Place</ORGANIZATION>,
self-conscious about his suitcase, developing a new tendency to glare
straight ahead when he passed any one. Several times he could have sworn
that men turned to look at him critically. He wondered vaguely if there
was something the matter with his clothes, and wished he had shaved
that morning on the train. He felt unnecessarily stiff and awkward
among these white-flannelled, bareheaded youths, who must be juniors and
seniors, judging from the savoir faire with which they strolled.

He found that 12 <ORGANIZATION>University Place</ORGANIZATION> was a large, dilapidated mansion, at
present apparently uninhabited, though he knew it housed usually a dozen
freshmen. After a hurried skirmish with his landlady he sallied out on
a tour of exploration, but he had gone scarcely a block when he became
horribly conscious that he must be the only man in town who was wearing
a hat. He returned hurriedly to 12 <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION>, left his derby,
and, emerging bareheaded, loitered down <LOCATION>Nassau Street</LOCATION>, stopping to
investigate a display of athletic photographs in a store window,
including a large one of <PERSON>Allenby</PERSON>, the football captain, and next
attracted by the sign "Jigger Shop" over a confectionary window. This
sounded familiar, so he sauntered in and took a seat on a high stool.

"Chocolate sundae," he told a colored person.

"Double chocolate jiggah? Anything else?"

"Why--yes."

"Bacon bun?"

"Why--yes."

He munched four of these, finding them of pleasing savor, and then
consumed another double-chocolate jigger before ease descended upon him.
After a cursory inspection of the pillow-cases, leather pennants, and
<ORGANIZATION>Gibson Girls</ORGANIZATION> that lined the walls, he left, and continued along <LOCATION>Nassau
Street</LOCATION> with his hands in his pockets. Gradually he was learning to
distinguish between upper classmen and entering men, even though the
freshman cap would not appear until the following Monday. Those who were
too obviously, too nervously at home were freshmen, for as each train
brought a new contingent it was immediately absorbed into the hatless,
white-shod, book-laden throng, whose function seemed to be to drift
endlessly up and down the street, emitting great clouds of smoke
from brand-new pipes. By afternoon <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> realized that now the
newest arrivals were taking him for an upper classman, and he tried
conscientiously to look both pleasantly blasé and casually critical,
which was as near as he could analyze the prevalent facial expression.

At five o'clock he felt the need of hearing his own voice, so he
retreated to his house to see if any one else had arrived. Having
climbed the rickety stairs he scrutinized his room resignedly,
concluding that it was hopeless to attempt any more inspired decoration
than class banners and tiger pictures. There was a tap at the door.

"Come in!"

A slim face with gray eyes and a humorous smile appeared in the doorway.

"Got a hammer?"

"No--sorry. Maybe Mrs. Twelve, or whatever she goes by, has one."

The stranger advanced into the room.

"You an inmate of this asylum?"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> nodded.

"Awful barn for the rent we pay."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had to agree that it was.

"I thought of the campus," he said, "but they say there's so few
freshmen that they're lost. Have to sit around and study for something
to do."

The gray-eyed man decided to introduce himself.

"My name's Holiday."

"<PERSON>Blaine</PERSON>'s my name."

They shook hands with the fashionable low swoop. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> grinned.

"Where'd you prep?"

"Andover--where did you?"

"St. Regis's."

"Oh, did you? I had a cousin there."

They discussed the cousin thoroughly, and then Holiday announced that he
was to meet his brother for dinner at six.

"Come along and have a bite with us."

"All right."

At the <PERSON>Kenilworth Amory</PERSON> met <ORGANIZATION>Burne Holiday</ORGANIZATION>--he of the gray eyes was
<PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>--and during a limpid meal of thin soup and anaemic vegetables they
stared at the other freshmen, who sat either in small groups looking
very ill at ease, or in large groups seeming very much at home.

"I hear Commons is pretty bad," said <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

"That's the rumor. But you've got to eat there--or pay anyways."

"Crime!"

"Imposition!"

"Oh, at <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> you've got to swallow everything the first year. It's
like a damned prep school."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> agreed.

"Lot of pep, though," he insisted. "I wouldn't have gone to <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION> for a
million."

"Me either."

"You going out for anything?" inquired <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> of the elder brother.

"Not me--<PERSON>Burne</PERSON> here is going out for the Prince--the Daily Princetonian,
you know."

"Yes, I know."

"You going out for anything?"

"Why--yes. I'm going to take a whack at freshman football."

"Play at <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>'s?"

"Some," admitted Amory depreciatingly, "but I'm getting so damned thin."

"You're not thin."

"Well, I used to be stocky last fall."

"Oh!"

After supper they attended the movies, where <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was fascinated by the
glib comments of a man in front of him, as well as by the wild yelling
and shouting.

"Yoho!"

"Oh, honey-baby--you're so big and strong, but oh, so gentle!"

"Clinch!"

"Oh, Clinch!"

"Kiss her, kiss 'at lady, quick!"

"Oh-h-h--!"

A group began whistling "By the Sea," and the audience took it up
noisily. This was followed by an indistinguishable song that included
much stamping and then by an endless, incoherent dirge.


   "Oh-h-h-h-h
    She works in a Jam Factoree
    And--that-may-be-all-right
    But you can't-fool-me
    For I know--DAMN--WELL
    That she DON'T-make-jam-all-night!
    Oh-h-h-h!"

As they pushed out, giving and receiving curious impersonal glances,
<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> decided that he liked the movies, wanted to enjoy them as the row
of upper classmen in front had enjoyed them, with their arms along the
backs of the seats, their comments Gaelic and caustic, their attitude a
mixture of critical wit and tolerant amusement.

"Want a sundae--I mean a jigger?" asked <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>.

"Sure."

They suppered heavily and then, still sauntering, eased back to 12.

"Wonderful night."

"It's a whiz."

"You men going to unpack?"

"Guess so. Come on, <PERSON>Burne</PERSON>."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> decided to sit for a while on the front steps, so he bade them
good night.

The great tapestries of trees had darkened to ghosts back at the last
edge of twilight. The early moon had drenched the arches with pale blue,
and, weaving over the night, in and out of the gossamer rifts of moon,
swept a song, a song with more than a hint of sadness, infinitely
transient, infinitely regretful.

He remembered that an alumnus of the nineties had told him of one of
<PERSON>Booth Tarkington</PERSON>'s amusements: standing in mid-campus in the small hours
and singing tenor songs to the stars, arousing mingled emotions in the
couched undergraduates according to the sentiment of their moods.

Now, far down the shadowy line of University Place a white-clad phalanx
broke the gloom, and marching figures, white-shirted, white-trousered,
swung rhythmically up the street, with linked arms and heads thrown
back:

   "Going back--going back,
    Going--back--to--Nas-sau--Hall,
    Going back--going back--
    To the--Best--Old--Place--of--All.
    Going back--going back,
    From all--this--earth-ly--ball,
    We'll--clear--the--track--as--we--go--back--
    Going--back--to--Nas-sau--Hall!"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> closed his eyes as the ghostly procession drew near. The song
soared so high that all dropped out except the tenors, who bore the
melody triumphantly past the danger-point and relinquished it to the
fantastic chorus. Then <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> opened his eyes, half afraid that sight
would spoil the rich illusion of harmony.

He sighed eagerly. There at the head of the white platoon marched
<PERSON>Allenby</PERSON>, the football captain, slim and defiant, as if aware that this
year the hopes of the college rested on him, that his hundred-and-sixty
pounds were expected to dodge to victory through the heavy blue and
crimson lines.

Fascinated, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> watched each rank of linked arms as it came abreast,
the faces indistinct above the polo shirts, the voices blent in a paean
of triumph--and then the procession passed through shadowy <ORGANIZATION>Campbell
Arch</ORGANIZATION>, and the voices grew fainter as it wound eastward over the campus.

The minutes passed and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> sat there very quietly. He regretted the
rule that would forbid freshmen to be outdoors after curfew, for he
wanted to ramble through the shadowy scented lanes, where <PERSON>Witherspoon</PERSON>
brooded like a dark mother over Whig and Clio, her Attic children, where
the black Gothic snake of Little curled down to <PERSON>Cuyler</PERSON> and <PERSON>Patton</PERSON>, these
in turn flinging the mystery out over the placid slope rolling to the
lake.

          *****

<ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> of the daytime filtered slowly into his consciousness--West
and Reunion, redolent of the sixties, Seventy-nine Hall, brick-red and
arrogant, Upper and Lower Pyne, aristocratic Elizabethan ladies not
quite content to live among shopkeepers, and, topping all, climbing with
clear blue aspiration, the great dreaming spires of Holder and <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>
towers.

From the first he loved <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION>--its lazy beauty, its half-grasped
significance, the wild moonlight revel of the rushes, the handsome,
prosperous big-game crowds, and under it all the air of struggle that
pervaded his class. From the day when, wild-eyed and exhausted, the
jerseyed freshmen sat in the gymnasium and elected some one from <ORGANIZATION>Hill
School</ORGANIZATION> class president, a <LOCATION>Lawrenceville</LOCATION> celebrity vice-president, a
hockey star from <ORGANIZATION>St. Paul</ORGANIZATION>'s secretary, up until the end of sophomore
year it never ceased, that breathless social system, that worship,
seldom named, never really admitted, of the bogey "Big Man."

First it was schools, and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, alone from <ORGANIZATION>St. Regis</ORGANIZATION>', watched the
crowds form and widen and form again; <PERSON>St. Paul</PERSON>'s, <PERSON>Hill</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Pomfret</LOCATION>, eating
at certain tacitly reserved tables in Commons, dressing in their own
corners of the gymnasium, and drawing unconsciously about them a barrier
of the slightly less important but socially ambitious to protect them
from the friendly, rather puzzled high-school element. From the
moment he realized this <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> resented social barriers as artificial
distinctions made by the strong to bolster up their weak retainers and
keep out the almost strong.

Having decided to be one of the gods of the class, he reported
for freshman football practice, but in the second week, playing
quarter-back, already paragraphed in corners of the Princetonian, he
wrenched his knee seriously enough to put him out for the rest of the
season. This forced him to retire and consider the situation.

"12 Univee" housed a dozen miscellaneous question-marks. There were
three or four inconspicuous and quite startled boys from <LOCATION>Lawrenceville</LOCATION>,
two amateur wild men from a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> private school (<ORGANIZATION>Kerry Holiday</ORGANIZATION>
christened them the "plebeian drunks"), a Jewish youth, also from <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, and, as compensation for <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, the two Holidays, to whom he took
an instant fancy.

The Holidays were rumored twins, but really the dark-haired one, <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>,
was a year older than his blond brother, <PERSON>Burne</PERSON>. <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> was tall, with
humorous gray eyes, and a sudden, attractive smile; he became at once
the mentor of the house, reaper of ears that grew too high, censor of
conceit, vendor of rare, satirical humor. <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> spread the table of
their future friendship with all his ideas of what college should and
did mean. <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>, not inclined as yet to take things seriously, chided
him gently for being curious at this inopportune time about the
intricacies of the social system, but liked him and was both interested
and amused.

<PERSON>Burne</PERSON>, fair-haired, silent, and intent, appeared in the house only as a
busy apparition, gliding in quietly at night and off again in the
early morning to get up his work in the library--he was out for the
Princetonian, competing furiously against forty others for the coveted
first place. In December he came down with diphtheria, and some one
else won the competition, but, returning to college in February,
he dauntlessly went after the prize again. Necessarily, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s
acquaintance with him was in the way of three-minute chats, walking
to and from lectures, so he failed to penetrate <PERSON>Burne</PERSON>'s one absorbing
interest and find what lay beneath it.

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> was far from contented. He missed the place he had won at <ORGANIZATION>St.
Regis</ORGANIZATION>', the being known and admired, yet <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> stimulated him, and
there were many things ahead calculated to arouse the <PERSON>Machiavelli</PERSON> latent
in him, could he but insert a wedge. The upper-class clubs, concerning
which he had pumped a reluctant graduate during the previous summer,
excited his curiosity: Ivy, detached and breathlessly aristocratic;
Cottage, an impressive mélange of brilliant adventurers and well-dressed
philanderers; Tiger Inn, broad-shouldered and athletic, vitalized by
an honest elaboration of prep-school standards; <PERSON>Cap</PERSON> and Gown,
anti-alcoholic, faintly religious and politically powerful; flamboyant
Colonial; literary Quadrangle; and the dozen others, varying in age and
position.

Anything which brought an under classman into too glaring a light was
labelled with the damning brand of "running it out." The movies thrived
on caustic comments, but the men who made them were generally running
it out; talking of clubs was running it out; standing for anything
very strongly, as, for instance, drinking parties or teetotalling,
was running it out; in short, being personally conspicuous was not
tolerated, and the influential man was the non-committal man, until at
club elections in sophomore year every one should be sewed up in some
bag for the rest of his college career.

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> found that writing for the <ORGANIZATION>Nassau Literary Magazine</ORGANIZATION> would get him
nothing, but that being on the board of the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Princetonian</ORGANIZATION> would
get any one a good deal. His vague desire to do immortal acting with
the <ORGANIZATION>English Dramatic Association</ORGANIZATION> faded out when he found that the most
ingenious brains and talents were concentrated upon the <ORGANIZATION>Triangle Club</ORGANIZATION>, a
musical comedy organization that every year took a great Christmas trip.
In the meanwhile, feeling strangely alone and restless in Commons, with
new desires and ambitions stirring in his mind, he let the first term go
by between an envy of the embryo successes and a puzzled fretting with
<PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> as to why they were not accepted immediately among the elite of
the class.

Many afternoons they lounged in the windows of 12 <ORGANIZATION>Univee</ORGANIZATION> and watched
the class pass to and from Commons, noting satellites already attaching
themselves to the more prominent, watching the lonely grind with his
hurried step and downcast eye, envying the happy security of the big
school groups.

"We're the damned middle class, that's what!" he complained to <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> one
day as he lay stretched out on the sofa, consuming a family of <LOCATION>Fatimas</LOCATION>
with contemplative precision.

"Well, why not? We came to <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> so we could feel that way toward
the small colleges--have it on 'em, more self-confidence, dress better,
cut a swathe--"

"Oh, it isn't that I mind the glittering caste system," admitted <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.
"I like having a bunch of hot cats on top, but gosh, <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>, I've got to
be one of them."

"But just now, <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, you're only a sweaty bourgeois."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> lay for a moment without speaking.

"I won't be--long," he said finally. "But I hate to get anywhere by
working for it. I'll show the marks, don't you know."

"Honorable scars." <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> craned his neck suddenly at the street.
"There's Langueduc, if you want to see what he looks like--and Humbird
just behind."

Amory rose dynamically and sought the windows.

"Oh," he said, scrutinizing these worthies, "Humbird looks like a
knock-out, but this Langueduc--he's the rugged type, isn't he? I
distrust that sort. All diamonds look big in the rough."

"Well," said <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>, as the excitement subsided, "you're a literary
genius. It's up to you."

"I wonder"--<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> paused--"if I could be. I honestly think so sometimes.
That sounds like the devil, and I wouldn't say it to anybody except
you."

"Well--go ahead. Let your hair grow and write poems like this guy
D'Invilliers in the Lit."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> reached lazily at a pile of magazines on the table.

"Read his latest effort?"

"Never miss 'em. They're rare."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> glanced through the issue.

"Hello!" he said in surprise, "he's a freshman, isn't he?"

"Yeah."

"Listen to this! My God!


  "'A serving lady speaks:
      Black velvet trails its folds over the day,
      White tapers, prisoned in their silver frames,
      Wave their thin flames like shadows in the wind,
      <LOCATION>Pia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pompia</LOCATION>, come--come away--'


"Now, what the devil does that mean?"

"It's a pantry scene."


  "'Her toes are stiffened like a stork's in flight;
    She's laid upon her bed, on the white sheets,
    Her hands pressed on her smooth bust like a saint,
    <PERSON>Bella Cunizza</PERSON>, come into the light!'


"My gosh, <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>, what in hell is it all about? I swear I don't get him
at all, and I'm a literary bird myself."

"It's pretty tricky," said <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>, "only you've got to think of hearses
and stale milk when you read it. That isn't as pash as some of them."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> tossed the magazine on the table.

"Well," he sighed, "I sure am up in the air. I know I'm not a regular
fellow, yet I loathe anybody else that isn't. I can't decide whether to
cultivate my mind and be a great dramatist, or to thumb my nose at the
<ORGANIZATION>Golden Treasury</ORGANIZATION> and be a <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> slicker."

"Why decide?" suggested <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>. "Better drift, like me. I'm going to sail
into prominence on <PERSON>Burne</PERSON>'s coat-tails."

"I can't drift--I want to be interested. I want to pull strings, even
for somebody else, or be Princetonian chairman or Triangle president. I
want to be admired, <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>."

"You're thinking too much about yourself."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> sat up at this.

"No. I'm thinking about you, too. We've got to get out and mix around
the class right now, when it's fun to be a snob. I'd like to bring a
sardine to the prom in June, for instance, but I wouldn't do it unless
I could be damn debonaire about it--introduce her to all the prize
parlor-snakes, and the football captain, and all that simple stuff."

"Amory," said <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> impatiently, "you're just going around in a circle.
If you want to be prominent, get out and try for something; if you
don't, just take it easy." He yawned. "Come on, let's let the smoke
drift off. We'll go down and watch football practice."

          *****

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> gradually accepted this point of view, decided that next fall
would inaugurate his career, and relinquished himself to watching <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>
extract joy from 12 <ORGANIZATION>Univee</ORGANIZATION>.

They filled the Jewish youth's bed with lemon pie; they put out the gas
all over the house every night by blowing into the jet in <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s room,
to the bewilderment of Mrs. Twelve and the local plumber; they set up
the effects of the plebeian drunks--pictures, books, and furniture--in
the bathroom, to the confusion of the pair, who hazily discovered
the transposition on their return from a <LOCATION>Trenton</LOCATION> spree; they were
disappointed beyond measure when the plebeian drunks decided to take it
as a joke; they played red-dog and twenty-one and jackpot from dinner
to dawn, and on the occasion of one man's birthday persuaded him to buy
sufficient champagne for a hilarious celebration. The donor of the party
having remained sober, <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> accidentally dropped him down two
flights of stairs and called, shame-faced and penitent, at the infirmary
all the following week.

"Say, who are all these women?" demanded <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> one day, protesting
at the size of <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s mail. "I've been looking at the postmarks
lately--<LOCATION>Farmington</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Dobbs</PERSON> and <PERSON>Westover</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dana Hall</PERSON>--what's the
idea?"

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> grinned.

"All from the Twin Cities." He named them off. "There's <PERSON>Marylyn De
Witt</PERSON>--she's pretty, got a car of her own and that's damn convenient;
there's <PERSON>Sally Weatherby</PERSON>--she's getting too fat; there's <PERSON>Myra St. Claire</PERSON>,
she's an old flame, easy to kiss if you like it--"

"What line do you throw 'em?" demanded <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>. "I've tried everything,
and the mad wags aren't even afraid of me."

"You're the 'nice boy' type," suggested <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>.

"That's just it. Mother always feels the girl is safe if she's with me.
Honestly, it's annoying. If I start to hold somebody's hand, they laugh
at me, and let me, just as if it wasn't part of them. As soon as I get
hold of a hand they sort of disconnect it from the rest of them."

"Sulk," suggested <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>. "Tell 'em you're wild and have 'em reform
you--go home furious--come back in half an hour--startle 'em."

<PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> shook his head.

"No chance. I wrote a St. <PERSON>Timothy</PERSON> girl a really loving letter last year.
In one place I got rattled and said: 'My God, how I love you!' She took
a nail scissors, clipped out the 'My God' and showed the rest of the
letter all over school. Doesn't work at all. I'm just 'good old <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON>'
and all that rot."

<PERSON>Amory</PERSON> smiled and tried to picture himself as "good old Amory." He failed
completely.

February dripped snow and rain, the cyclonic freshman mid-years passed,
and life in 12 <ORGANIZATION>Univee</ORGANIZATION> continued interesting if not purposeful. Once a
day Amory indulged in a club sandwich, cornflakes, and Julienne potatoes
at "<PERSON>Joe</PERSON>'s," accompanied usually by <PERSON>Kerry</PERSON> or <PERSON>Alec Connage</PERSON>. The latter was
a quiet, rather aloof slicker from <PERSON>Hotchkiss</PERSON>, who lived next door and
shared the same enforced singleness as <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, due to the fact that
his entire class had gone to <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>. "<PERSON>Joe</PERSON>'s" was unaesthetic and faintly
unsanitary, but a limitless charge account could be opened there, a
convenience that <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> appreciated. His father had been experimenting
with mining stocks and, in consequence, his allowance, while liberal,
was not at all what he had expected.

"<PERSON>Joe</PERSON>'s" had the additional advantage of seclusion from curious
upper-class eyes, so at four each afternoon <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>, accompanied by friend
or book, went up to experiment with his digestion. One day in March,
finding that all the tables were occupied, he slipped into a chair
opposite a freshman who bent intently over a book at the last table.
They nodded briefly. For twenty minutes <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> sat consuming bacon buns
and reading "Mrs. <PERSON>Warren</PERSON>'s Profession" (he had discovered <PERSON>Shaw</PERSON> quite
by accident while browsing in the library during mid-years); the other
freshman, also intent on his volume, meanwhile did away with a trio of
chocolate malted milks.

By and by <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s eyes wandered curiously to his fellow-luncher's book.
He spelled out the name and title upside down--"<LOCATION>Marpessa</LOCATION>," by <PERSON>Stephen
Phillips</PERSON>. This meant nothing to him, his metrical education having been
confined to such Sunday classics as "Come into the <LOCATION>Garden</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Maude</PERSON>," and
what morsels of <PERSON>Shakespeare</PERSON> and <PERSON>Milton</PERSON> had been recently forced upon
him.

Moved to address his vis-a-vis, he simulated interest in his book for a
moment, and then exclaimed aloud as if involuntarily:

"Ha! Great stuff!"

The other freshman looked up and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> registered artificial
embarrassment.

"Are you referring to your bacon buns?" His cracked, kindly voice
went well with the large spectacles and the impression of a voluminous
keenness that he gave.

"No," <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> answered. "I was referring to <PERSON>Bernard Shaw</PERSON>." He turned the
book around in explanation.

"I've never read any <PERSON>Shaw</PERSON>. I've always meant to." The boy paused and
then continued: "Did you ever read <PERSON>Stephen Phillips</PERSON>, or do you like
poetry?"

"Yes, indeed," <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> affirmed eagerly. "I've never read much of
<ORGANIZATION>Phillips</ORGANIZATION>, though." (He had never heard of any <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> except the late
<PERSON>David Graham</PERSON>.)

"It's pretty fair, I think. Of course he's a Victorian." They sallied
into a discussion of poetry, in the course of which they introduced
themselves, and <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s companion proved to be none other than "that
awful highbrow, <PERSON>Thomas Parke D'Invilliers</PERSON>," who signed the passionate
love-poems in the Lit. He was, perhaps, nineteen, with stooped
shoulders, pale blue eyes, and, as <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> could tell from his general
appearance, without much conception of social competition and such
phenomena of absorbing interest. Still, he liked books, and it seemed
forever since <PERSON>Amory</PERSON> had met any one who did; if only that <PERSON>St. Paul</PERSON>'s
crowd at the next table would not mistake _him_ for a bird, too, he
would enjoy the encounter tremendously. They didn't seem to be noticing,
so he let himself go, discussed books by the dozens--books he had read,
read about, books he had never heard of, rattling off lists of titles
with the facility of a <ORGANIZATION>Brentano</ORGANIZATION>'s clerk. <PERSON>D'Invilliers</PERSON> was partially
taken in and wholly delighted. In a good-natured way he had almost
decided that <ORGANIZATION>Princeton</ORGANIZATION> was one part deadly Philistines and one part
deadly grinds, and to find a person who could mention <PERSON>Keats</PERSON> without
stammering, yet evidently washed his hands, was rather a treat.

"Ever read any <PERSON>Oscar Wilde</PERSON>?" he asked.

"No. Who wrote it?"

"It's a man--don't you know?"

"Oh, surely." A faint chord was struck in <PERSON>Amory</PERSON>'s memory. "Wasn't the
comic opera, 'Patience,' written about him?"

"Yes, that's the fella. I've just finished a book of his, 'The Picture
of <PERSON>Dorian Gray</PERSON>,' and I certainly wish you'd read it. You'd like it. You
can borrow it if you want to."

"Why, I'd like it a lot--thanks."

"Don't you want to come up to the room? I've got a few other books."